He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
Firstienach, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons.
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage
with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show focused on
Enchantment in creation the union of the scene and unseen
as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Greetings, giant killers, dragon slayers,
masher of monsters.
Christ is risen, he truly is risen.
Although when you hear this episode, it will be the ascension, actually.
You psyched yourself out on that one.
I know, I know, I know.
But it's Christ is risen where we are here in the past.
You all still be risen on Thursday.
That is true.
That is true
And descendant you are listening technically correct, which is the best kind of true
It's the kind that endures you to all your friends and family when you're technically correct
Yeah, and that's how you know your listening to the Lord of Spheres podcast
My co-host the very reverend doctor almost double doctor
multi-masters. Stephen DeYoung is with me from Lafayette Louisiana out there in
the swamp and I'm here.
from the much drier and much less humid,
it may as Pennsylvania.
My name is Father and just Stephen Damick.
And we're not live today.
This is a pre-recorded episode as already referenced
because Father Stephen is traveling when this one airs.
In fact, this is going to be pre-record month here in 2024
because for the second episode of June,
I'm going to be traveling.
So, you know, we're not abandoning you.
We're preparing for outside chance.
I will actually be live on YouTube doing something else
while this is air.
That could be fun.
That always feels like I am not going to look at the comparative streams
because I refuse to believe that I am better than me.
I feel like there's a William Shadner reference in here somewhere, but it's just not coming to be.
Oh, oh, there it is.
Yeah, yeah.
Mirror universe.
Okay, audience work on the joke throughout the episode.
All right.
Yeah, so in this episode we're continuing to talk about apocryphal second temple Jewish texts and this time
We're talking about the ascension of Isaiah and the assumption of Moses. Don't mix them up
These texts straddle the time of the birth of Christ and very much blur the conventional distinctions a lot of people having their heads between Jewish and Christian texts
And for those of you who've listened to this podcast for a long time
These texts will include some elements that we have mentioned many times
So it should be a lot of fun, but even if this
This is your very first episode because we know for a lot of people, for every episode,
some episodes is their first episode.
This should still be fascinating, I think.
So you don't have to have listened for a long time in order to get this one.
So this is actually really the enoc episode, finally, right?
No.
I mean, so if we still have to do the show for a while, I guess.
Still forthcoming, yes.
And even fifthcoming.
Yeah.
Yeah, it might worry people like when the first thing I can
episode actually comes out. People will probably panic thinking it's the last episode.
It'll be a sign of the apocalypse, but this is an apocalypse.
It will be. Yeah. It couldn't have been the last episode.
This isn't apocalyptic episode. This is this is an episode of out of apocalypse as well, right?
Yeah, not like the Egyptian mutant dude. No.
You know, there are podcasts about him. The movie version of that was very disappointing.
Yes, especially since Oscar Isaac is actually a good actor.
I know. But yes, that was the laymas and Salvador. But I have to say he is not the best
X-Men villain in the first place.
Oh, apocalypse? No. Yes. Yeah. Like I mean, he has an awesome backstory and stuff and everything.
Yes. Yes. But and he has his four horsemen who are like cool and all. Very cool. And like,
but I don't know. I may be the only one who back in the day was reading, you know, Walton
Weezy Simonsons x
factor when they're introducing him and he was like this lurking evil in the background.
I remember that. His name is Apocalypse, right? And like, you know, it's set up all this stuff.
This guy's going to be super awesome, you know, and everything. And then they finally go
to fight him and like, he turns his fists into giant blue mallets.
Oh man, I blocked that out.
And it's like, come on, this is Sandman level.
stuff but saying man did it yes yes like come on this is excellent dude we already had like
Magneto right who is who is the greatest excellent villain of all time period well yeah
and what about what are the greatest villains all right and then like you know oh here's
gonna be the new big bad and it's you know right plastic man I don't know
I don't know.
What?
I'm going to move you out here at the beginning of the episode.
A should plastic man.
But this isn't a possibility episode.
Things will be revealed.
But I mean, at least he looked better than than Mr. Sinister, who kind of looks like
Arnold Schwarzenegger, Cosplaying is Robert Smith.
Anyway, we're slightly off topic.
I think this is the second episode in a row where we've we've led off with Marvel Comics
references with X-Men in particular.
Yeah, well.
Well, next bend 97.
came out. Right. Kind of makes you crazy. Let's say it kind of makes you wonder whether
whether a lot of these, you know, classic X-Men writers were reading Second Temple Jewish
literature and that's where they're getting all their ideas from. Pretty sure Chris Claremont
never read any Second Temple Jewish literature. Chris Claremont, as he's still living, if
you're listening, Chris, write in. He's not. Write in. We want to hear from you. What do
Think about the book of two leases that were you got
I mean, come on, come on man.
So I've met a ton of classic comic creators.
The only one who was ever rude to me in person
was Chris Clarevon.
Wow.
I'm not going to tell the whole story here
because it's way off topic.
But he's the only one who was ever like rude to me.
Maybe I'll get you to do that when you appear
someday on my YouTube channel.
Maybe.
Yeah.
We can talk about whatever we want there.
Well here too, but.
I met him a couple times.
One time he was just kind of abrupt and curt with me,
and I'm Dutch, so I'm used to that.
The other time he was actually rude.
Especially because half the guys who are Dutch are named Kurt anyway
Well, there's more birds than Kurt's I think of the no
Dutch listeners let us know that's right right?
This is the problem with pre tapes we feel those sense of urgency. I know I know because we're not live
Just truth is looking somewhere in the background in the studio like putting on her headphones once while oh, they're still going
Yeah, we hear a foot tapping or something
Exactly.
Body wanders by.
When am I?
to get to use that line. So what are we talking about again? Ascensions, assumptions,
hints and allegations, all of the above. Incidents and accidents. All the above. So we want to make some
here at the beginning we want to make some distinctions. Okay.
In terms of this overall area, right? So what for example is the difference between an ascension
you
and an assumption.
You can make an assumption, but not you can't just make an
assumption.
It's grammatical, right?
Well, you could make an assumption.
You could do it by ascending.
You ascend, but I don't think you make an ascension.
Like that's not the word.
You could say I'm going to do an ascending.
That's an a little awkward.
I don't know.
You have to just say I ascend.
Yeah, but then after you've done that, you can refer to your
ascension. Hey man okay okay.
Okay, so trying to get me on a technicality here.
It's not working.
Because the best kind of correct is technically correct.
Technically correct.
Yes.
Ascension and assumptions, right.
Are two different related things, right?
So when we talk about an ascension, we're talking about a bodily ascent, a la in the
old testament, enic and Elijah.
So these guys are...
key distinction still alive. Still alive bodily taken up into heaven. Now we didn't include
Christ in that. We will be talking about Christ's ascension actually into certain point later on.
Which is good. A little bit here. This episode will air on the feast of the ascension.
So yeah, but that goes sort of way beyond what happens with the economic Elijah indeed and we did a whole episode
about it. So, yes, you can go and look that one up if you want to hear us go on and on
about that one in particular, but here we're talking about humans, right? Regular humans.
So that's a bodily still living ascending to heaven, enigma, and Elijah are examples. And then
there are assumptions. And when we talk about an assumption, like the assumption of Moses that we're
We're talking about...
about tonight, we're talking about someone who has died,
and then their body is taken up into heaven.
So in a way, an assumption is sort of an early resurrection,
meaning their body, since it's being taken up,
is reunited with their soul sort of in advance
of the general bodily resurrection of everyone.
Right.
And so, of course, there's a longstanding tradition that we're going to talk about tonight,
about the assumption of Moses that is sort of recorded in the text that we call the
assumption of Moses.
We'll get more into that.
Yes.
And there's, of course, also that tradition regarding the Theotokos within the church
that after her death, her body was assumed to heaven, the Mother of Christ, who is also
the mother of God don't come at me with your story and not because Christ is God. Yes.
So these are sort of slightly different, right? One is they're still alive, taken up into heaven.
The other is a person dies and their body is taken up meaning taken up and reunited with them.
So the question, the key distinction is, has the person died or not?
Right, right.
in the past. So we're not going to spend a ton of time because it's not totally
germane to the two texts that we're talking about tonight. Talking about Enic and Elijah in
detail, we have in the past talked in more detail about them and their sense to Heaven, especially
in our episodes about saints.
And we'll be coming back to obvious
Please.
Enoch, maybe less obviously to folks Elijah later on as we continue this series on and off
talking about Second Temple text because of course Enoch, as you know, has a number of them
named after him in a whole genre of literature named after him.
But there's also an apocalypse of Elijah, for example.
So and that sort of leads into what we more want to talk about.
If you want to read those texts, Genesis 5, 20, 21 through 20.
talks about Enoch's being taken up into heaven and second kings to verses or
fourth kingdoms to one through 14 talks about Elijah but in terms of how those
ascents sort of come to function in terms of later Jewish and Christian
tradition and Second Temple Jewish literature.
Those, as sense, are seen as...
occasions for apocalyptic visions? Right, because if you think about it, like here's a person
who's being taken up into heaven, it's a very natural question like, so what did you see?
Why you were there? Right. Right. And so it is we've talked about apocalyptic does not mean
end of the world per se. Yeah, just unveiling. It means a revelation. Right, something is revealed.
build. So the gazette build, right.
And so, if they're going up into heaven, not only are they seeing what's in heaven, in the place where they go,
wherever else they go, on some kind of cosmic journey, but they're also seeing, and this is kind of important for the text we're talking about tonight again,
as it has been for some of the other ones we talked about.
They're also seeing the earth and what's going on on the earth and the history of the earth, from that perspective.
Yeah, exactly from the perspective of heaven. Now you can see this world in a
way from that point of view.
And so all apocalyptic literature by definition
involves someone taking that kind of journey.
And so when you have these two figures from the Hebrew
Scriptures who were told we're taking up into heaven,
that then presents this good opportunity
for apocalyptic literature to be composed.
and become attached to those figures.
This also sets up from the perspective of later literature,
the idea that, well, since they didn't die,
they're just sort of taken up into heaven,
this then is seen to present the opportunity
that they could come back, they could reappear.
And this, so for example, with Enoch,
eventually when we do that first Enoch episode,
We'll talk about in some of the later sections that aren't in all the versions, but in some
of the later sections, for example, Enet comes back and appears to Methuselah or appears
to Noah to communicate things to them.
Since he didn't die, it was taken up into heaven, he could reappear in bodily form and interact
with him, interact with his descendants.
And of course, not only within scripture, but outside of scriptures, there's all kinds
of Jewish tradition about the return of Elijah, right?
From leaving a chair open for him to Elijah coming first before the Messiah, right, that
he didn't die.
He's taken him into heaven, so now he's going to come back.
And there's even Jewish hymns to Elijah, calling upon him.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Is that an idol tree though?
No.
Oh, by the way guys, it's not how my dollar tree works.
Yeah, exactly.
And then we also see an image here.
And this takes off, for example, from some of the details,
like the detail that the Prof. Elijah St. Elias is taking
up into heaven.
in a chariot, this is connected to the idea of God's chariot throne.
We talked about this more in our episodes about saints.
But so these two men from the Hebrew Scriptures come to represent
sort of the image of what a redeemed human being looks like.
Yeah.
That they were sort of, they experienced salvation to such an extent in this life
that they didn't die.
And they were taken up into heaven and then
because of the idea of the chariot throne,
they're sort of included in God's divine counsel,
sort of immediately, along with the angels.
And even those reappearances, like Enex reappearances,
are sort of connected to the, he's doing the kind of things
that God would send an angel to do.
Yeah.
Right, to convey, to convey messages,
he's sort of functioning as an angel,
sense of functioning as a messenger.
Right, of God.
And you see that connection also with the Elijah traditions, both in the Hebrew scriptures
and around it, where he's coming before the Messiah to bring some message to announce,
right?
Sort of the coming Messiah again, that's a kind of angelic mission, which is why sometimes
he say John the Forerunner with Angel wings.
Yeah, well, and also why, like when, when the Lord on the cross
as Ali Ali, there are people who,
now that means my God, my God,
he's referencing the Psalm 22,
but why there were some people who could think
he's calling upon Elijah,
because that's a thing that people were doing.
Yes.
Yeah.
You don't actually keep justifying your idolatry.
Yeah, it's also very interesting that when Christ says that he says it in Aramaic, it's
that he's quoting a Psalm, right?
It's a quoted in Hebrew.
Or Greek.
Yeah.
Sorry, Greeks.
I have to be...
Is that our first sorry Greeks on the show? I don't... I can't remember
I don't know. I feel like I've picked out the Greeks at some point. Although that may have just been
taking them taking me picking on Plato personally. I don't know.
But then I say nice things about Aristotle sometimes. So they're probably torn.
They don't know what to do with me. So those are, you know, people who we see who has said,
now we mentioned when we were talking about assumptions where someone dies and their body is taken up,
up the old testimonies.
example we refer to was Moses. Yeah. Moses dies. This may not be super obvious to some
people that that's what's going on there. So we're going to talk about that. Yeah. So like
with Enic at Elijah, I mean Enic, just reading those verses in Genesis, there's a little ambiguity.
Yeah. If you really start parsing the words, it becomes
plain pretty quickly. Well, right. I like what's going on. Yeah. It says, like it says, God took him.
He won't...
walked with God and got to took him.
But then you get a nice disambiguation in Hebrews 11
where it says by faith,
Enoch was taken up so that he should not see death.
Right, and there's also,
well, you get similar things in Ben Sirac and wisdom also.
So I mean, that's just,
everybody interprets it that way
from the earliest interpretations we have.
Right, yeah.
God took it.
But even then, you don't even have to rely on that.
You could just dig into those verses and Genesis.
the word that's take is sort of more like...
transplanar, transly. But anyway, yeah, so there's a little ambiguity there, but I mean, it's
pretty clear what's going on. Not many people would argue with you about either of those cases
that the Bible is saying they were taken up into heaven. Sure. Right. There are some weirdos
about Elijah but if you're one of those weirdos who I just call the weirdo
I'm sorry man, but you're being a weirdo.
And so this is an email. We love the weirdo emails.
Yeah.
A lot actually.
Like this is just so abundantly clear what's going on.
But yeah, there was somebody.
Even if I remember the day by what's saying,
who was saying that they were trying to warp it around to be God took a line
to put him on an island or something.
Oh, there is a thing out there.
Yes, you can-
Actually, as I was researching a little bit for this, there is a thing out there that said that basically God sucked him up into heaven and put him somewhere else so they could administer somewhere else for a while.
Yeah, which is kind of a quasi-mormon thing or something.
Yes, I don't know.
I don't know.
Was it the US? Is that where it was a Jackson, Missouri?
It's a very pretty part of Missouri.
Yeah.
And that's just weird.
Right?
not even the Jackson Missouri part, like the rest of it.
Right? Because it's so clear what's going on in the text.
It's so clear how everyone from the original readers on
understood that.
Yeah, you know, got to write journal articles and stuff, though.
So hey, um,
they won't publish your article if you're just saying like,
everything you thought was true is actually.
Yeah, but anyway the case of Moses is much more ambiguous if you're trying to just go by
Just strictly by the couple of verses that describe the death of Moses
Right, it's not obvious. It's especially not obvious in English the way it's usually translated in English. Yeah
Right, this is a Deuteronomy 34 verses 5 and 6. Yeah, so it says this
That's what death of Moses is described. So Moses the servant of the Lord
died there in the land of Moab.
according to the word of the Lord, and he buried him in the valley in the land of Moab, opposite Beth Pére,
but no one knows the place of his burial to this day.
Yeah.
So,
right off the bat, even before we start asking questions of it, there's some weird things in the text.
Like, it tells you where he was buried and it says, no one knows where he was buried.
Yeah.
maybe they just mean it somewhere in this valley
We don't have the actual gravy.
Steve's odd.
But there's also some, now what are these you can't see, right?
But I pointed out to Father Andrew when he did the good old cut and paste on the quote.
And that's that in most English Bibles, for some reason, the he and he buried him is
not capitalized.
So who is this he that buried him?
Well in the context, you can go back to the beginning of chapter 34.
There's not a bunch of other humans here.
It doesn't talk about Moses and Joshua hanging out and talking or something, so that might be Joshua.
It's the verses leading up to this are all the Lord, meaning Yahweh talking to...
Moses, right before he dies.
There's nobody else mentioned in there.
And so when it comes up to Moses, the servant of Yahweh,
dies there, the land of Modab, according to,
it could just be with the word of the Lord,
meaning who he was talking to,
and the Yahweh who was standing there talking to him.
And he buried him.
The he can-
only refer to the Lord, or specifically the word of the Lord, right?
Yeah.
Being the one who buried him, right?
So God is the agent here of Burying Moses.
Okay.
There we have to ask another question.
And that is what is the word buried?
their mean. I might say, well, buried, that's obvious. You know, you'd take a hole, you
put the body in cover with dirt. That's what you think. Right. But the word that is translated
is buried in Hebrew, here means in general to care for a dead body.
Yeah, I mean, which we do.
that in English too, right? Like I've many times said, oh, I buried that guy last year.
But I was not the one who dug the grave. I was not the one who put the body in the grave.
I, you know, led the funeral services. Right. Right. And when that word is used elsewhere
in the Hebrew Scriptures, like what is it? Someone just go bury your dead. That doesn't
mean that doesn't mean, oh, just throw them in a hole. That's it. Like you're not allowed
to do anything right that means goat
take care of the bodies of these deceased people, right?
So
And then finally, right at least the English translation the father Andrew read
You know, which causes were think he buried him in this place
But no one knows the place of his burial
right
Makes it extra confusing the second one is a different word. It's no one knows the place of his grave
to this day.
So you could also read it as he, meaning the Lord, did his funeral in the valley of the land of Moa, but no one knows the place of his grave, you know.
Yes, cared for his body, right, to care of his dead body in that place, but no one knows where his grave is.
Right.
And so, again, from the
the earliest Jewish interpreters we have,
they understood this to mean that God,
when it says that God is taking care of his body,
it's that God took his body, right?
That God took his body, meaning he took it into heaven, right?
And while that is never explicitly said
in the New Testament, right?
It never straight out says in the New Testament,
God took Moses' body into heaven.
This tradition is very clearly referred to in the New Testament.
The first time is a little oblique because the first time is on Mount Tabor at Christ's Transfiguration.
We all know that scene. The Lord appears. He goes up there with Peter, James, and John.
And then he's transfigured in front of them. And while he's transfigured in front of them, Moses and Elias stand there talking to him.
Right.
Yeah.
And we've heard that so much that we miss the point that would have been weird if you
didn't know about this tradition.
Right?
Because as we've already said, Elijah coming back, sure, right?
Didn't die.
Right?
Bodies up in heaven.
They're expecting him to come back.
We're multiple times, right?
But usually when you get two people showing up,
it's Enic and Elijah, right?
Enic is the other one who went up into heaven without dying.
Right?
And so you can see this, if you read,
if you read the earliest interpretations we have
of the book of Revelation, right?
Revelation is saying John, you'll see that pretty much everybody says
says with the
two witnesses who show up, the two witnesses that Relation talks about are Enic and Elijah.
Right? The two guys who left, the two guys come back, right? And then they interpret that
in different ways, whether it's literally Enic and Elijah, whether that's representative
of Christ and say, John the four-runner, there's different places they go with that, right?
After that. But that's the identification they make, because that was, that's sort of
the natural identification.
even in a lot of Jewish literature, right?
But anything that's in the orbit of this tradition about Moses,
then what happens on the Mount of Transfiguration makes sense,
because Moses has also been reunited with his body.
Right?
Right, the story of the Mount of Transfiguration doesn't say,
you know, Elijah and the ghost of Moses.
Right?
Elijah and the Spirit of Moses
Elijah and the soul of Moses.
They're both presented there as being bodily,
as being recognizable.
So they have the sense of identity about them,
such that the disciples know who they,
Peter James and John know who they are.
Right?
Know that that's Moses and Elijah.
It's almost like they'd seen pictures
of them somewhere before.
It's not a solitary thing.
But they saw Moses.
Sorry.
Moses was visible, right?
He's yet his body.
Yeah.
So this is assuming that tradition.
And then even more clear than that, right,
without even having to dig much,
you get Jude, verse 9.
Right.
If his little saint Jude, brother of the Lord.
Yeah.
This is one of those ones that
If someone is into the weird bits...
in the Bible, they probably have seen this a lot, but if they're not, they probably have
may not even remember that this is there. So yeah, Jude 9, there's just one chapter in Jude,
so just Jude 9. But when the Archangel Michael contending with the devil was disputing about the
body of Moses, he did not presume to pronounce a blasphemous judgment but said the Lord rebuked you.
you. So there's no like, it doesn't tell the story. He's like, Oh, you know, like when,
When when when
the Archangel Michael and the devil were disputing over the body of Moses. You remember that? Yeah,
he doesn't say, oh, and one day, when Moses died, that kid doesn't tell the whole story.
Just sort of assumes that the audience knows the story.
Yeah. I think Saint Jude's epistle was inspired to be the thorn in the flesh of all those who
believe in Soluscriptura. He wants to quote and reference everything except the Bible.
He does refer to Sodom and Gomorrah so not completely but
Just quotes first, the edic verbatim, etc.
And refers to this, right?
Reference to this.
And we'll come back to this where we talk about the text, the assumption of Moses.
But we can already go ahead and say here,
we don't know for sure that this is a reference or the Lord of the Euku is a quote.
We don't know for sure that that's a direct reference
to the text, the assumption of Moses. In fact, it probably isn't. It could be, but this is a
reference to the traditions that we have recorded in the assumption of Moses. And notice how,
yeah, as Father Edger said, how Saint Jude refers to it, he just refers to it off head,
like, yeah, you all know about this, right? And he does it bother to say, oh, I know this isn't
the Bible is just a tradition but because that's not the way it up.
He could just refer to it as an example.
And so clearly this is telling us, again, this doesn't, as I mentioned, explicitly say God
took Moses' body into heaven. But this is very clearly, we'll see some more about that
a little bit but this is very clearly a reference to this trid-
Now why would St. Michael, the Archangel, and the devil be fighting over Moses' body?
Right, and what does it mean for God to take it?
Yes.
This isn't, as some people, especially those infected with Play-Doh brain.
St. Michael and the devil contesting over the soul of Moses.
Yeah, it's about this isn't Moses passing through an aerial toll house.
Okay.
This is they're fighting over his body.
Over his body, not his soul or his spirit here.
That's what the contention, the dispute.
Right.
is over. So why is this? Well, first of all, because they're fighting about the body,
this tradition is assuming the bodily resurrection. Right, because if there is no bodily resurrection,
who cares? Yeah. Why would you fight over? You just be fighting over his soul. Right. Right.
30 did to be a fight.
Right.
Just to show man.
But so this assumes the bodily resurrection. This assumes that the body is in some sense still Moses
Right, and it needs to be protected or you know claimed right
It also though
Assumes that the devil because there has to be a contention the devil
Has some claim to press over the body of Moses
That was us.
Right.
And this goes back to something we've talked about a few times on the show,
regarding the curse that's placed on the devil in Genesis chapter 3.
And we've talked about how it says, you know, you're going to crawl on the ground and eat
the dust of the earth, all the days of your life.
And certain very literal-minded people want to read that is,
Oh, this is right here.
story about how the snake lost its legs. I still remember some weird fundamentalist tracks where
they were claiming they had evidence that snakes he stabbed legs. I tried to prove that this was a
true story scientifically. Like really guys? Because of course as we've said before ancient people
had seen snakes eat mice. Right. Right. At rats. They'd see this app. They knew they didn't need dirt.
right?
And the word that's used for the dust that the snake is going to eat is the same word
that just a few verses away is used when God says
You are dust and to dust you will return to Adam
It's made for dust he's gonna return to dust
So this is talking about the decomposition of his body. Yeah, this is this is talking about the devil is the eater of the dead
Yep, yep
This is dissolution, you know.
this integration death corruption decay.
Right.
Entropy.
And it expresses physical corruption.
Right.
The physical corruption of the body.
That this is sort of a punishment.
And so, the devil is trying to claim Moses' body and corrupt it.
Right.
But as Moses is a righteous man, right.
St. Michael is disputing this claim.
in this scene that St. Jude refers to.
Yeah, the idea being that the devil
who has been swallowing up the dead all this time,
now Moses dies, he's like,
great, here's a tasty morsel.
And the Archangel's like, hold on a second.
Right.
Yeah.
And so,
in this tableau,
even though I
we don't have this whole story spelled out here in St. Jude's epistle. It's
hard to imagine that St. Michael would have lost this particular engagement.
Yes, right. Right, and unfortunately that time the devil won. Right, no, right.
That's not gonna happen. Right. So then, again, we're just kind of
if I was a H.J. but assuming St. Michael wins this...
particular contest, which is particular dispute. I mean, given tabour, I'm pretty sure that
it's right. Like what happens to Moses body, right? That's why this is directly connected to this
assumption tradition and to resurrection. And this is a mode of reasoning, this that we've just
been talking about that we don't talk about a lot, even the Orthodox Church, though we have more,
a little more reason that we'll talk about a minute to talk about it.
But is important very early on at least in the Christian Proclamation.
And as evidence of that, you have what St. Paul says in Acts 13, 35 through 37,
where he quotes David in the Psalms saying, you will not allow your holy one to see decay.
Yeah, right about decaying in the tombs and and David there's very clearly you read the whole song
for which that's quoted. David is talking about trusting in God even though he dies and goes to
shalt all right goes into the grave right so it's very much pointing to the bodily resurrection
right in in the psalm but after quoting it uh St. Paul then says you know David after he had done
that everything he did is God's servant died and decomposed.
Right. Right. So David had not yet literally experienced the resurrection. Right. Even though he had put his trust in his faith in it, he had not yet experienced it. Right. And then, say Paul uses that to point to Christ, whose body did not see decay during his entomment because he rose from the dead. Right.
that ends.
So St. Paul is there using his mechanisms to talk about Christ's resurrection as the beginning,
the first root of the general resurrection.
The Christ's resurrection is the resurrection.
Right? And that's connected to this idea that his body did not at any point to K.
Because Christ says in St. John's Gospel, he says the rule of this world is coming for him, he has
has no claim over here.
right, he finds nothing in him. He has no claim on Jesus. And so the things that are
pitted against each other are the resurrection versus corruption. Yeah. That's
that's what the fight between Michael and the devil is about. Yeah, decayed and and decomposition.
and this is what's going on with.
There are certain saints in the Orthodox Church, whose
relics, whose bodies are pretty sure we talked about this back in the relics episode,
way back in the log of go time.
Don't decay, or at least don't decay normally.
Yeah, and there's there's there's variation in this point like there's levels of this.
On the one end you've got bones that maybe turn golden or scarlet and have a fragrance,
beautiful fragrance. That's kind of the most the most minimal form of an
corruption. And then on the other end, you've got the hand of St. Mary Magdalene, which not only has a flesh on it and it's flexible, but it's also warm, which I probably have, I think I've mentioned this on the show before, but I can personally attest to that.
Like I have actually touched it for myself and can attest that that is real.
Yeah, so that's these are,
Incoreoperelics are a sign of
of the bodily resurrection, of the reality of the bodily
resurrection.
It's incomplete, but it's present on some love.
Right.
Yeah.
So then, we talked about this Moses tradition.
We mentioned back at the beginning that this is not only
something, a tradition that the church has received about
about most.
But this is what we say also happened with the Theotokos.
Right. So if someone says, well, why do you believe that the body of the Theotokos was assumed in heaven?
And we can say, oh, it's just like Moses.
Yeah. Then they get confused.
Right. So if they've never heard or considered it in a set that we just finished talking about.
Yeah. Yeah. And we're also going to have to do a little bit of disambiguating vis-à-vis
the sub
of Mary in the Roman Catholic Church. And I know already, you know, I know it's gonna be a section of
you Catholic listeners who can insist that we're misrepresenting you and etc. etc. Here's a thing.
We love you and we care about you Roman Catholic listeners to the show, but
But there seems to be
be this thing among Roman Catholic people, even Roman Catholic people who I get along
with totally well, that they're unable to acknowledge that any summary of their doctrine
and beliefs that is even vaguely critical is accurate.
Well, I mean, that's that's a human thing, right?
But it's especially yeah.
Print.
out among a lot of programs.
I think that that's true.
And part of humility, right, part of humility,
intellectual humility, is being willing to admit
that there are people out there who fully understand
what you believe.
Orthodox people need to do this too, by the way.
I'm not just saying there's Roman calendar.
Orthodox people, Protestant people, right, Buddhists, right?
Republicans, everyone needs to, right?
understand this. Right. Yeah, libertarians. Right. Everyone needs to. An arco-communist.
You must all understand this. Right. Zero-astrians.
We have to be willing to accept that there are people out there who fully understand what I believe,
or what you believe. Completely understand it just as well as you do. Right.
and don't agree with it.
Yeah, the other two things that I think people need
to toss aside that kind of go in the same direction as,
the assumption is if you don't agree with me,
number one, it could be like,
it's the other person doesn't understand it, right?
So there's, yeah, you don't know.
Right, yeah.
And that could be either that they're ignorant,
so they haven't studied enough, right?
Or it could be that they're incapable of understanding it,
like you're just too stupid.
And then that.
one is you have an ulterior motive, right? It's your evil. And so you don't want to accept this,
right? But the reality is that people can look at all the same evidence, be just as informed,
they can be just as smart and just as good-willed and still disagree. It's a reality.
Yeah. And that's okay. That doesn't mean you're wrong.
Right. Doesn't mean you're wrong. You could still be wrong, but that doesn't mean you're wrong.
But
That is automatically mean you're wrong.
Right.
That's, I mean, so you can argue about it.
You can argue why you're right and they're wrong or whatever.
Right.
But present evidence, whatever you want to do.
But you have to accept at some point, not everyone who
disagrees with you is stupid.
Not everyone who disagrees with you is uninformed.
Not everyone who disagrees with you is lying.
Yeah.
Not every-
What do you disagree with you as arguing with bad faith?
I mean, to me, the conversation's only really good interesting.
Once you assume none of those things are true,
then you can have an interesting conversation, right?
Yeah, yeah.
And that's not to say no one who disagrees with you
is ignorant or stupid or acting in bad faith.
There are certainly those people out there, right?
Absolutely.
And when you discern one of those people,
it's not worth arguing with them.
Right.
It's just a walk away.
just let them be right
But there are those out there who do have good faith disagreements with you
And those are the people as you said who are interesting to actually talk to about it
So it worth while to talk to about it. We sent all that to say this
To say that to set up for the fact that we're gonna have to do some disambigate in here
Yeah, point to some areas of disagreement
Right, then our legitimate disagreement because I also you know
So everyone who knows we know how much
despise the pan-heresy of ecumenism. We're also not willing to do this paper over like,
oh, we all just really agree. We'll just terminology. Yeah. And no, there are points
to disagree with. We're both very much on record of not thinking that way. I think there's
only like five people in the world who are real Christians. That's how opposed to the
the Panthers need to be cute with his a way up.
And I'm not.
one of them. That's right. That's good. And me, we have their prayers. Pies to
regress. We just lost several listeners there. But that's okay. That's all right.
Yeah. As long as they're not over those five, those five would listen to the show.
That's the thing.
Yeah.
So, okay.
In terms of what the church...
By that we mean the Orthodox Church says about the theotokos vis-a-vis her body being assumed
to have an after-her-death.
So we have to start out in terms of talking about this.
By talking about the fact that our starting point is that it happened.
And here's what I mean by that, right?
I don't mean it happened because it happened, right?
What I mean by that is...
There's this tendency nowadays in conversations.
So I'll use another example related to the Theotokos,
because this is one that has come up a lot at least around me.
And that's over the fact that the Theotokos didn't give birth to any other children besides Jesus.
which is something that was believed by everyone in the church until...
like late 17th century.
Yeah.
And, you know, just to throw the prize
that Reformers believe in.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
And just to throw this out, especially for those of you
who do believe in Soloscriptura,
there is nowhere in the New Testament
that it ever describes any other person
as being a child of Mary.
Yes.
So, if you're gonna say she had other things.
Well, we're not gonna, yeah.
You're gonna have to go outside the Bible.
Just let's not litigate that too far, though.
Yeah, no, no.
But I'm just saying, I'm just, yeah.
I'm just using that as an example, right?
Yeah.
Right, right.
And the example I'm using it for is not the issue itself,
but the argumentation surrounding it.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
So, but it's very common,
even though this is a relatively recent thing
to reject that idea and to say that she did give birth
to other children.
This is the majority view among evangelical Protestants
of the United States now, I would say.
Yeah.
Right.
And when someone,
probably, I mean, I don't claim to have any kind of great knowledge of conversations
between Protestants and Roman Catholics, but I imagine with them, and I know for sure
in conversations between Orthodox folks and Protestants on this issue, Evangelical Protestants
at least.
The way it's often approached from the Evangelical Protestant side is the argument starts
with not...
is that factually true or not?
The argument starts with, well, why?
Well, what does it mean?
Why is that important?
The pthiotocosis is ever-perfect.
That's where the conversation begins.
And therefore, the argumentation,
if you track it out over the course of the conversation,
like if you took a transcript of the conversation
and tracked the course of the argument,
of course.
argument from the other side tends to be you can't give me an adequate or acceptable to me explanation
of why or what it means or why it's important. Therefore I reject that it's true. Yeah.
Right? Therefore, I reject that it's true. And there's the problem with that is that
all of these things, all of these events in and around Scripture which relate
to the Christian tradition in our faith, including the very most important ones,
the central ones all happened first. They just happened and they didn't happen in
way that explained to themselves.
And then after the fact, the church reflected on those things and the wise and the what it means and the why it's important,
comes out of that later reflection.
So to use a couple of the very most important and central things of the Christian faith, as examples, Christ rose from the dead.
That's as central as you get. That is the central proclamation of Christianity. Christ has risen.
Right. Christ rose from the dead. That did not come with an explanation. Right.
In and of itself. Right. Right. At the time Christ rose from the dead, his disciples so didn't get it that they didn't think he was going to rise from the dead. Right.
Yeah, they should have because
told them, right? They gothuls, but they didn't, right? They not only didn't have an idea of what it meant,
they didn't even know it was going to happen when it happened. They found out about it after it
happened. And when they first heard about it after it happened, they didn't believe it. Right?
Then later, after this has happened and after Christ has appeared, right? It explained a little bit
at least. Right?
what it was about, you get St. Paul writing first Corinthians 15 about the resurrection
and reflecting on Christ's resurrection. And other passages all through the New Testament,
all through the writings of the Church Fathers, all through the writings of the Church in every
era is reflecting upon, right? That's what real theology, if we're talking about theological writing,
is. Right, it's not coming up with new new
arguments and do stuff, right?
It's reflecting upon who Christ is and what he's done, right?
And the experience of Christ.
So, right, you see this pattern, it happens to the understand it.
We can say the same thing about the crucifixion.
Right, Christ is crucified.
Christ dies on the cross, right?
Pretty central to the whole Christian faith, right?
But at the top
time, no one understands why it's happening. In fact, there are pretty much everybody
misunderstand what happened there at the time. After the fact, again, huge portion of the
New Testament is reflecting on the meaning of Christ's crucifixion and death. And then
again all through the history of the church, all this reflecting upon it.
So...
explanations and understandings come afterward. So when I say that the beginning of
what we're saying about the Theotokos and her body being assumed into heaven is
that it happened. We're saying that we have had handed down to us from the eye
witnesses who saw it. The fact that after the Theotokos died after she was buried
They return
to the tomb to care for her body and her body was gone. Yeah. Okay. And when they
returned to the tomb and her body was gone, it was not like when Jesus rose from
the dead in the sense that she was not walking around eating with them, right,
that she was resurrected in the same sense Jesus was, right. But her body was
gone in the same sense that Moses is.
was. Yeah. Right that she had already experienced resurrection, but she's not walking on this
earth. Now that does and has historically opened up the possibility that she can make
return appearances. Just like my life. Yeah. But right. So this happened. They've had
Hey, her body isn't here.
And I'll also point out that with all the claims of relics, the most interesting thing
to me that John Calvin ever wrote, at least the most entertaining, we'll put it that way,
is at one point, John Calvin wrote an inventory of all the relics in Western Europe as best
he could ascertain it.
And it's him doing his best Jonathan Swift before Jonathan Swift because...
He's kind of making it obvious like did St John the Four Runner have eight legs in three heads?
right
Right to point out that these all can't be legitimate. So there were people there were rackets
Oh, yeah, it varies parts of the Christian world at various times selling fake relics. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah
Okay, we're trying to set up fake pilgrimage sites with fake relics shows up in Chaucer
It's yeah, it's endemic, right throughout chrysendom. Yeah
Right.
from St. Constantine on, it becomes just endemic, pops up all over the place, okay?
There's no record anywhere of anyone ever claiming to have a body part of the Theotokos.
Yeah, which there'd be very strong reasons to do that.
Yes.
Yeah.
There's never a claim.
And I mean, never a claim.
We don't even have like, oh, this bishop had to send a letter saying, hey, this is phony
because her body was taken up into heaven.
No whatever even claimed it in the first place and had to be corrected.
Which shows how incredibly deep seated this belief.
Yes, how early and how deep seated and how universal this understanding was within the
Christian church, right, from a very early phase.
So yes, it happened and then after...
the fact that they happen, it gets interpreted and it gets interpreted in light of these Moses traditions.
That, oh, what happened with Moses happened with her.
Right, that God took her body so that it would not see corruption.
Because she was a righteous servant of God like Moses was.
Yeah.
Right, and is of course the mother of the Lord.
Okay.
Now here's where our Roman Catholic friends will again get irritated with me.
Some of them will even call this an attack, but there's nothing I can do about it.
So here we go.
How dare you sir?
It is very obvious even though we celebrate the Dormition, the Falling asleep,
meaning the physical death of the Theotocos on August 15th.
That's the same day the Roman Catholic Church celebrates the Assumption of Mary.
Right.
It's on the same day. It was proclaimed a dogma in the 19th century by the Roman Catholic Church,
the assumption of Mary. And when it was declared a dogma, actually, I'm going to have to
to arm actually you.
Oh is it the 20th?
Yes, yes.
A fiction of,
so you're thinking of the Amaca conception.
That's 19th century.
The Magical conception was after anyone.
1950. 1950. Oh see. I'm going to I'm going to I'm going to I'm going to revel in this for just a second because I almost never get to match
Lee you. Okay. Okay. So 20th century later than that even it's a good dog. Yes I flipped my Marion dog.
us. Um, we'll see now they're all going to use this as evidence. See he doesn't know
what he's talking about. You got to date wrong. Bust. Yeah. Um, so.
So in the proclamation of it as a dogma, Rome deliberately introduced an ambiguity to try
to include us in the East.
Now, as I said, this is pre-Vaticant too.
So it wasn't so much that they cared about us as that the way a proclamation of dogma
works in the Roman Catholic Church is that they declared that some particular belief was
Held always.
everywhere and by everyone in the church, which is super fascinating with the immaculate
conception and Thomas Aquinas.
So they're saying that what they were proclaiming is dogma about the assumption of Mary was always
everywhere held by everyone in the church.
And they were aware of at least in broad strokes.
The difference between...
the tradition in the east on this and what they were declaring.
And so they put this nambulous little phrase because what they were declaring as dogma
effectively is that the Theotokos, the mother of the Lord, the mother of God did not die,
But ascended into heaven.
and ascended it to heaven in a manner parallel to Jesus' ascension, to Christ's ascension.
Yeah, and interestingly, like, if you actually read, if you read the text,
right, of this dogmatic decoration by Pope Pius XII, which is named, I'm going to get this wrong,
but munificentism is Deus. That's pretty good. They link it directly with the Amactic Conception.
Yeah, right. It actually says.
that she completely overcame sin by her immaculate conception.
And as a result, was not subject to the law of remaining
in the corruption of the grave, and she did not have to wait
until the end of time for the redemption of her body.
So there's, it links it to this,
to that earlier Catholic dogma of the immaculate conception.
Yeah.
And you notice the language there.
So unlike Moses, there wasn't,
she didn't have to die and there didn't have to be a fight.
Yeah.
Right.
So she ascends it to Heaven.
and linked in the way it's celebrated in the iconography of the feast in the Roman Catholic Church,
is when I say it's paralleled with the ascension of Christ, I don't just mean flying up into the sky, right?
Because although Elijah and Edic potentially with Edic, but flew up into the sky, right?
What I mean is, as we talked about in our ascension episode,
Christ's ascension is really about His enthronement.
Yeah, if you look
the celebration of the Feast of the Assumption of Mary in the Roman Catholic Church.
It's really about the enthronement of Saint Mary as the Queen of Heaven.
Yeah, and I mean, if you just want to check this, just go to Google Images and type in Assumption
of Mary, and it'll show you a gazillion Roman Catholic paintings.
And you can see this is her being enthroned in the heavens.
Right. And then you can search for Dormition of the Theotokos, which will show you the Orthodox icon.
Yeah, we're...
where you see her dead body, you see her dead body on the bottom center and
Christ with her soul in his hand right above the body. So the door mission icon is very clear
that she physically dies. Right. And so being at least somewhat aware of this
and wanting to make the claim at least semi-legitimate that this is what was always in
everywhere believed by everyone when it, you know.
There is an ambiguity introduced into the dogmatic crop
collimation by Rome that she may or may not have died.
Right. Even though clearly from everything that is said,
like the quote that Father Andrew just read from all the
iconography associated with it in the West, they're saying she
didn't. Right. Like they're saying she did not. But they
introduced that ambiguity so they can try and rope in all of
the Eastern Text.
that all of the Easter discussion of it.
These quotes say Jonathan Damascus and various other things.
As evidence in support of what they're proclaiming,
even though it's different, right?
And so there are some fundamental differences there.
Right, there are just some fundamental differences there.
Now we don't deny, as Orthodox Christians,
we don't deny that Queen of Heaven is an appropriate title
for the Theotokos, right?
You can listen to our, we did an episode about the Theotokos talking about her as Queen and Mother.
Right?
Queen Mother.
Yeah.
Um, so, you know, that it's not that we to die, the title is appropriate, but we think there's
something fundamentally different going on with the Dormitia Theotokos and what's going
on to the assumption.
That's in part linked to the immaculate conception also, um, which we do reject fully.
Uh
And our concern with that in the Orthodox Church is that pretty much exactly what summed up in that quote father Andrew read that you're making the Theotokos something other than a human.
And because Christ takes his human nature from the Theotokos, if she's something other
than a human descended from Adam.
like the rest of us, then what does that mean about Christ's humanity?
That his humanity is different than the humanity of the rest of us.
Yeah. And I mean, the whole thing falls apart.
I think it's worth noting, by the way, that if you look up Roman Catholic explanations of this
dogma, you can find different opinions about whether or not the Virgin Mary actually died.
And that's because that ambiguity is there.
because the ambiguity is there.
You're allowed to believe either.
But all of the positive statements, the hemnography, the iconography, and all of those things,
right, are pointing to the other in one direction.
But there's that language again. You're allowed to believe
the other.
And
this is what we're getting into when this issue comes up. What are the first things?
between Roman Catholic and Orthodox folks.
One of the first things you'll hear from the Orthodox side is that for us, it's not a dogma.
And I think that gets misinterpreted a lot.
It gets misinterpreted a lot. Part of the reason for that is
is what the Roman Catholic Church means by dogma.
And how Protestantism has traditionally reacted to that.
Because especially, as most of these conversations are happening in places like the United States
and Canada, right, and the Anglicone World, that are dominated by Protestants
and then minority Roman Catholics and then tiny minority Orthodox, right?
Most of these conversations that are taking place that we have access to are taking place
between Protestants and Roman Catholics and they're usually
in a North and Ox person to be seen, right?
Like the vicinity.
And so, the Roman Catholic view is clearly
that anything that's a day-feet-a-dogma,
which would include, since mid-20th century,
the assumption of Mary, which includes the Maccala conception,
includes all those things that have been proclaimed as dogma.
Definitely dogma.
You have to believe it or you can't go to heaven.
In very brief form.
Yeah, necessary to.
It's a decision.
Yes.
Now, there are, you know, again, because no matter what I say, I'm going to be accused
of misrepresenting the Roman Catholic position.
I have quoted the catechism of the Catholic Church, and been accused of misrepresenting
the Roman Catholic position.
But it's amazing I don't give up.
But
There are qualifiers like this only applies after the dogma has been declared.
So for example, Thomas Aquinas didn't really believe in the immaculate conception, but it
was declared a dogma like 600 years after he died.
Which, I mean, let's think about that for a second.
You must believe this in order to be saved, but if you didn't use to believe it before
the dogma was declared, you could be saved.
suggesting that salvation now works differently.
Right. Because there was a great reason.
Right. Because now if you don't believe it, you are rejecting the truth.
So that's the distinction that's understood. Okay. Okay.
Right. So Thomas Aquinas was just got to ignore it. Yeah. So he'll be all right.
In his place and time, he didn't know, right? Yeah.
How important this was. And right. And so if you're ignorant because it hasn't been made a dogway yet,
or if you're just ignorant in general, like if you're living somewhere in the world and you've never heard of it,
you
Right. But the idea is if you're aware of it, so if you're saying a Protestant and you've
read the decree and you've heard about it and you reject it, you can't go to heaven.
That's the official teaching. Right. I know post Vatican II, we've all gotten mushy
about everything, but that's still the official on the books in Latin teaching, right, of Rome.
If you were consciously
Jacked, where these dog was, you can't go to heaven. And of course, the Protestant response
to that is like, what? These things that aren't the Bible, first of all, obviously, because
Protestant's generally hold to some form of solar scriptura. But so because of that kind
of debate, the debate then shifts. That would have argumentation shifts the overall debate
to what are the things you have to believe.
in order to get into heaven. Or, yeah, reversing that, what are the things that denying them would
cause you to not go to heaven? Right. Yeah, technicalities. Well, yeah, but not just technicalities, but
it creates this kind of minimalism. Right, right, exactly. Right, like you're trying to compose mere
Christianity for example. Yes, that shots fired CS Lewis.
I don't think that's a good impulse.
Yeah.
I want minimal Christianity.
No, I want more Christianity, right?
I want all of Christianity.
That's the bike.
Yeah.
I want the whole thing.
I don't want the turkey sandwich.
But this idea of we need to just whittle down what are the bare minimum things, right?
some of this is in reaction to
you know, here comes the bug bear again, the idea of a humanism, right? I want to
will this down enough that I can so that I can call more people my brothers,
hands across, and so forth. And and opt out of theological debates and stuff
because I'll decide those aren't really important, right?
But this has all kinds of bad effects.
This has all kinds of bad effects.
And this slides in only one direction.
The direction this slides in is fewer and fewer things get important with each generation.
There are these folks out there. You can find them on the internet.
They're called reformed baptists.
Reform Baptist, their Baptist Suerch Calvinist.
meaning their Baptist who hold to a theology formulated by people who killed
Baptist's heretics. I know. It's amazing. Right? So this issue, not baptizing
your children, was such a serious issue in the 17th century. People were killing
each other over it.
Right?
And now Presbyterians and Reformed Baptists
go to the same seminaries and they call each other brothers
and they both hold to the Reformed faith
that oh, it's not that big a deal.
Right?
Both Luther and Calvin believed that a Baptist church
was not really a church.
They believed that a Roman Catholic church
could be called a church,
but that the Baptists were a sect.
they were worth
that Roman Catholics, according to Lutheran Calvin. Right? But now, hey, we're all friends.
And now that this sliding of what's important, now that we're in the 21st century and we're down
to almost nothing, and it's gone from just theological issues like how you formulate the Trinity,
or who Christ is.
which are now up for grabs, apparently.
It's gone for that.
Now that it's gotten into moral issues and ethical issues,
now all of a sudden a lot of our Protestant friends
are realizing the problem.
Right, to be blunt, now that it's,
oh, who you have sex with isn't really all that important.
Now there's an issue.
Tastantly denying the doctrine of the Trinity,
Dr. Nathanael Trinity, 30 years ago, we just started winking at.
But now that it's gone into this moral zone, now it's serious, ironically.
But it's not going to go in the other direction, guys.
When you start whittling down what is mandatory about the Christian tradition, it's going
to be less and less.
It's going to be mandatory with each generation.
And now we're pretty much at the point as we've said before on the show where what it means
to be a Christian is.
is I identify as a Christian.
Yeah.
It doesn't matter what I believe, it doesn't matter how I live.
If I just identify as a Christian, I am a Christian, and you have to acknowledge that
or you're a bad person.
You can't tell me I'm not one.
Based on how I live or what I believe or what I do or where I go to church or if I never
go to church or if I start my own in my garage.
Yeah.
Right?
That's where that leads.
Yes Lewis did not want it to leave
there. Right. Right. I'm not blaming him for it. Yeah. Right. Yeah. But that's where that's where it leads.
Right. That's where it leads. But it starts on a very personal level. It starts with individuals,
this idea that again comes out of the Reformation of, oh, if you tell people they have to believe these
things. The teaching you something about the history of the church that isn't...
in the Bible, literally plain as day,
can't question it, can't doubt it.
So teaching you about the fact that,
hey, did you know that after the Theotokos died,
her body was taken up into heaven.
I am somehow imposing on you.
I am binding your conscience.
Yeah.
I think, you know, that's one of the reasons,
that's one of the things I see this a lot
because a lot of the work I do is aimed at evangelism.
And so people ask the question like,
well, do I have to believe that
in order to be
North of Ox Christian. And I mean often the short answer to most of those questions is yes,
but the I think the more important answer is, look, do you want to be part of this community?
Do you want to live this life? Because I mean, as I've found, especially when I was doing pastoral
ministry that conviction actually tends to follow conditioning, that the things
that you believe
actually tend to flow out of the way you live and what you're participating in
rather than being the prerequisite for that. You know like I and it works the
other way too like I've watched people for instance who were faithfully
Orthodox and then they for one reason or another they started to attend another
church like one example that I know of for instance a family member asked them would
Please come with...
me or take me, you know, all the time. And it wasn't that they had like a conversion experience
while they were there, or that they suddenly realized, hold on a second, I no longer believe
this and I now believe this, it's that the habit of being in that other church turned
them into that. And then all kinds of sort of doctrinal explanations followed. But it wasn't
like hey I had a you know I came to an awareness of I don't I disagree with this now and I
agree with this and so therefore I'm going to go over there.
And that's why there's also this whole phenomenon.
I see this a lot too.
People say, oh, I agree with all this stuff,
but I just can't bring myself to walk through the door.
I agree with all of this, or even people who
call themselves Orthodox, but have never actually
even been to an Orthodox church.
That's, there's this disjunction.
It's this notion that Christianity is a list of things
that you get.
As you said, like boxes that you check off,
I agree I disagree.
You know?
Yeah, the core of it is that
It's not a question of what you believe. It's a question of who you believe right?
Yeah, and
Who are you faithful? Yes, yes, and even folks who are out there who are all about the individual conscience
Right
Ultimately, you're believing somebody
You're not coming up with all this yourself as the man said you got to serve somebody
Okay.
Yeah.
Right like and you're not just saying and I know there are people that well, I believe the scriptures
Okay, someone's explaining them to you. Yeah
You're believing someone's explanation and it's for a variety of reasons, right?
And I'm not just saying this if you're not orthodox or the docs people too. Oh, yeah, right
You know if people when if if they are pressures in my church and I get up in preach
And I preach about what you know reading from
The Gospel of St. John means, right?
And they believe it.
They're trusting me.
They have for various reasons decided that they can trust my
explanations of these things.
Right?
It could be a variety of reasons among the different members of my congregation.
So this isn't just, again, this is everyone.
This is every human.
You are believing someone.
Right?
You are trusting someone.
Someone's explanation.
with someone's interpretations.
Right, and for various reasons.
Right, the various reasons why you accept person A's as opposed to person B's or group A's as opposed to group B's
Right, you may or may not be aware of them at any given point in time. You may be very aware of them
Maybe very conscious of them. It may be related to decisions you've actually made or
That may be kind of sub-rosa kind of unconscious or subconscious with you and you know
But if people believe things
because they were true, no one would ever be wrong.
They'd always believe the truth, right?
So we have all these other reasons.
And so you're addressing.
And so that's the real question we have to ask.
There's some danger here, because if I set up myself
as the judge of all things, I'm going
to hear from the representatives of all these different views
and then I'm going to decide for myself who is right
I want the right thing to do.
is or the right way to go is, right?
Scripture's tell us there's a way that seems right to a man
and it's in his destruction.
We should remember that, right?
So I can't just trust my own judgment.
My own judgment is flawed and sinful by definition.
I need others, right?
And so we're going to choose to submit to something
to be a part of something to receive.
something to enter into a Christian tradition, right, that existed before we were born.
If it didn't exist before you were born, just don't even think about it.
It's not worth it.
Right.
We got made up last weekend.
It's wrong.
I assure you.
Right.
And that's what we submit to.
where people say things to me or around me.
like, well, I agree with a lot of stuff
of the Orthodox Church or the Orthodox Church seems good
to be in these various ways.
But for example, this is something I heard someone say,
if I join I'd have to pretend I believe some other things
that I don't believe, that wouldn't be authentic
or something, right?
Yeah.
No.
That's not what the Orthodox Church,
I'll speak for the Orthodox Church as an Orthodox priest.
That's not what the Orthodox Church calls you to do.
I'm sorry.
The Orthodox Church does not call you to agree or pretend to agree to on a list of things in order to be a member
But the Orthodox Church requires you to do is to not make that decision for yourself
But the Orthodox Church requires of you if you decide to join the Orthodox Church is that you decide this is Christ's Church
This is the place where Christ is
This is the place where I encounter him.
Therefore, what...
Christ's church teaches is what I will believe.
No matter how it seems to me,
some of it may make total sense to me
and some of it may not make any sense to me,
but I'm gonna believe it either way
because this is the place where I encounter Christ.
This is Christ's church.
Yep, amen.
All right, well all that said,
we're gonna go ahead and take our first break
and then we'll actually start diving into these texts
this episode is about.
So, whoop.
be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
You've probably heard of St. Rafael Halloweeny saying to Alexander Hodovitsky,
liturgical translator Isabelle Habgood.
and other righteous men and women who made their mark on the early development of Orthodoxy in America.
But what about the notorious, itinerant Bulgarian monk, or Father Rafael Morgan, the first black Orthodox priest in America?
Or Vera Johnston, who served the Orthodox Church without renouncing hertheosophist roots.
There are stories in many others, some edifying, some appalling, all entertaining,
Make up the lost histories of the early decades of Orthodox
Christianity in the continental United States.
Lost histories, the good, the bad, and the strange in early American Orthodoxy by Matthew
Naney, out now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
the young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
And we're back.
So we just been an hour and 25 minutes.
Setting up the framework for the two texts we're going to be discussing,
which are the ascension of Isaiah and the assumption of Moses.
Or is it called that? We'll get to that.
Uh, uh, or his-
But yeah, that is your real name.
Yes, exactly.
Exactly, ancient texts if that is your real name.
Yeah.
It's important to understand the difference between an ascension and an assumption.
And the basic thing that they turn on is whether the person is dead or not.
If they're alive still and they're caught up into heaven, it is an ascension if they're dead
is it is an assumption of their body.
And this is, this is the orthodox take on this.
We said there's the Roman Catholic.
and there's ambiguity built into that,
and you can find all kinds of explanations of that.
So, go look that up for yourself if you want to read
all about the way that the Catholics explain
what happened there.
But yeah, so the first of the two texts we're going to talk about
is the ascension of Isaiah.
So, I mean, we know who the prophet Isaiah is,
but it turns out there's actually a whole bunch of traditions
surrounding him that are not mentioned explicitly in the Old Testament,
And some of which then these these not old test
traditions get mentioned in the New Testament, right?
They're nearby.
Yes, they're.
Scripture in the.
Yes.
Yeah.
So the ascension of Isaiah is.
And this is something we already talked about this actually with the the testaments of the 12
But we'll find this with a lot of these texts as they've come down to us a lot of
these things that we refer to, oh this is a second-templar Jewish text. The written documents we now have
are sort of often multiple texts put together, like amalgamated, where not just a composite of
oral traditions, almost all of these are repositories of pre-existing oral traditions, but
But...
actual written tax that have been put together, right?
And or iterated upon.
And what we now call the ascension of Isaiah
actually has three different pieces that have been put together.
The main body of the text is sort of in two pieces
that were originally two separate pieces.
And then another chunk of text has been kind of
pushed in the middle. So it's three texts put together, but it's not sort of like text
one, text two, text three. Yeah. It's text one and text two, and then text three is kind
of rammed in to the middle of text one toward the end, off center. But we'll talk about
that more in detail here in a minute.
So using that numbering text one followed by text two and then text three squished in text one the first piece is
a second-templed Jewish text
Meaning it's it's
Jewish as opposed to
Reflecting any Christian emphasis right and and probably dates to before Christ
We're not
No, probably not.
It's probably contemporaneous with some of the earliest writings of the New Testament,
like a couple of St. Paul's epistles.
Yeah, that's the problem, by the way, folks.
Like we often refer to second-temple Jewish texts, but as a distinct category from, say,
the Old Testament and the New Testament.
But the reality is that the New Testament itself is a set of second-temple Jewish texts.
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, that doesn't necessarily mean not Christian because Christianity was a Judaism
Along with a whole bunch of other right Judaism's that were around in that period
So just yeah, just just just take note that we're using shorthands that are not perfect. Yeah, yeah
So what we're really saying here is that that first part
had
Non-Christian Jewish origins right there's there's no indication in this part that it is from within the Christian community
Yeah.
On the other hand, and the reason we're making that point is that the other two pieces are very definitely Christian.
Right. Now we've talked about in terms of the other texts, we've only talked about a few so far, but even the ones we've just talked about.
We've talked about how there are times where scholars, anytime they see that looks even, anything that looks even vaguely Christian.
They're like, oh, Christians added that.
like knee jerk.
That's a Christian interpolation.
Christians added that.
Christians changed that.
Right?
And we've seen that in a lot of times those are silly.
Like, if you presented them the book of Isaiah,
like the canonical book of Isaiah, and you didn't tell,
and you told them it was from, you know,
say the third century.
They didn't know it was the biblical book.
They probably claimed that a bunch of things
were Christian interpolations because they sound Christian.
Yeah.
Right?
There's stuff that sounds...
Christian all through the Old Testament, guess what?
Right.
So we've talked about how that's kind of something.
So when we say here that these other two pieces
are very clearly Christian, we're not doing that.
Like, they are way too on the nose.
Like, one of them uses the phrase, the Christian church.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
Okay, Christian's, Rufurscal, Christian's,
and Antioch, right?
Like, that's a Christian document.
five minutes.
talking positively about the Christian Church
is something they're a member of, right?
And the other one isn't quite that explicit,
but talks about things like, you know,
the apostles going and evangelizing.
Yeah.
I mean, so it's like, yeah.
So all three parts come from the second half
of the first century AD.
Okay.
So, these things including the Christian parts.
the two parts that we're calling Christian parts.
We're written during the time when
the
a lot of the new test modes being written.
So that's important to keep in mind.
This is the stuff we're calling Christian material here is not like
later Christian material.
It is as early as and earlier than some of the books of the New Testament.
The three parts were put together in the form that we have them now,
sometime early in the second century,
in the first half of the second century.
That took its current form.
We know that because we start finding citations
of the
text in the second century, in the shape that it's in now. So this is as early as it gets.
As you be a partner, remember, we see some of the content of the Christian sections, by the way.
But it is a composite like that. So part one, right, piece one, the non-Christian Jewish part,
And again by that by the fact that I'm saying non-Christian
Do not assume that that means anti-Christian. Yeah, right
It just means it came from a Jewish source and the Jewish
Source that produced it was not a Christian
So there's no like antipathy to Christianity or anything here
And it doesn't seem to have been edited
by whoever, right? Someone could have whoever put it in its
current form with all the Christian pieces in it and on it, right? Could have gone through and
edited this part, right? If they wanted to, they could have gone and made it like really obviously
Christian too, but they didn't. Right? They didn't. So the fact that they didn't
And shows you that it's definitely not anti-Christian.
I do like it's not contradictory.
And it feels the need to.
They felt like they could just add to it.
They didn't need to change anything.
So this is what makes up chapters 1 through 5.
And a note here, I wanted to do this earlier, but I forgot.
When we give chapters and verse numbers on these texts,
we're almost always, there are exceptions,
but almost always going back Charles Worse's numbers.
which these are not necessarily universal.
Right. And we're doing that because every time people have asked us where to get these texts,
we point them to the two volume Charles worth Old Testament suit a pygrifat. So since that's what we
point people to, those are the numbers we use. Right? Almost always. Sometimes there's pieces of
texts that aren't in Charles' worth or something. And so we have to do something a little different.
But almost always we're given where using Charles' worth.
Those are not standard.
right? Like chapter adverse divisions are new enough to the Bible, but with the Bible,
everybody has kind of agreed on them. With these texts, everyone who's published a translation
has done their own numbering. Literally. Yeah. And part of the reason for that, part of
reason for that is that some of these tax exist in multiple forms.
So eventually when we do the one on first enich, there are radically different in length
versions of the book of enich in different languages of first enich.
And so if you tried to follow the same numbering scheme, it would be a mess.
Like in the shorter versions, if you're translating one of the, if you're translating to say
the shorter Greek version. Greek version is much shorter than the
the
the Haraq version. Then you'd have to figure out how to use the numbers, right? Like, do I skip
verse numbers? When there's material that's left out of the shorter version? So I go like
verse 27 and then verse 33. People don't notice, I think it's weird, right? So there's a reason
for that. Everybody just numbers the version that they're translating.
So that means that if you have some other translation other than Charles worth and you try to look up this stuff based on the numbers we're giving.
You know, you might not have a good time. You might be like, wait, that doesn't say anything about that. Right.
That's why.
And you don't need to send us emails or anything. I mean, Father Andrew always loves getting emails. But always.
You don't have to send his e-bills saying that's not what verse blankity blank says.
right because you're reading a different version that's because you're reading a
different version. Right. Save yourself the time typing it even if you don't
care about Father Andrew Spam folder. So yeah so we're going by Charles
Worcett numbering. So this is chapters one through five right the first section
this is where for just the martyrdom of Isaiah and this is basically a written
record.
of earlier Jewish traditions regarding the death of the prophet Isaiah, right?
So his death is not recorded in the book of Isaiah.
Yeah.
Or in the books of the kings.
So that's not recorded in the Old Testament, the Hebrew Scriptures, but there was a,
we say, traditions, remaining orally handed down memory of how he died and when he died,
right?
Because he had disciples who compiled the book of Isaiah.
Right.
people
who are going to know about how he died and tell the story of it because he's a very
well-known and loved and revered prophet.
And this is one of those examples where here's a tradition represented in one of these
kinds of texts that is also represented in the New Testament.
And not saying that the New Testament gets it from this text in this particular case,
Right? But that they're both representing stuff that's not in the old
So the fact that Isaiah was sawn in two and that's how he died he died as a martyr.
That's the detail that you find in this text and also in Hebrews 1137.
And also in the Talmud. It's also in the Talmud.
Well the Talmud is a little different.
Yeah. Okay.
Because so Hebrews just makes a reference to an old testament state being so sawn in two.
Yes, that's right. It doesn't explicitly say that it's a day.
It does explicitly say it's Isaiah and there's no elaboration of the story.
Like how did that happen?
Who did it?
Yeah.
Why?
Right?
There's not like a whole story there.
It's just a reference to these traditions.
That's especially why we can't say it has anything to do with this text.
Right?
Right.
That basic idea that that's how Isaiah died obviously was going around in oral tradition
completely separate from this written text.
the Talmud.
when it talks about the death of Isaiah, actually follows and includes more information from the story as it's told in the Margaritum of Isaiah in these chapters.
Okay, so it seems that the Talmud version then is pretty clearly dependent upon this text that we're talking about.
Well, or very close to it.
Yeah, or they maybe have a common source perhaps.
Yeah, yeah.
So we can't say for sure, but much more closely related to it than it had more of the deep
and more of the shape of the story, right, is there the Talmud?
That's part of the reason, by the way, that we say that this part comes from a non-Christian Jewish source,
because if it came from a Christian, even a Christian Jewish source, it's unlikely that the Talmud would pick it up unaltered.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, right. This is part of the general reservoir of Jewish tradition, not...
the specifically Christian strand of Jewish tradition.
So basically what happens in terms of the narrative is that Hezekiah dies.
Isaiah has revealed to him that Manasseh is going to become king of Israel. Manasseh is a bad dude.
We have the tradition as represented in the prayer.
of Manasseh, a little piece of extrabiblical content that Manasseh
eventually repented. But for most of his life, he was exceedingly wicked and sort of brought back
paganism, full force in Israel. So Isaiah kind of realizes this is going to happen as forewarned
because he's a prophet. And so he takes the community of the prophets, which was a thing.
and
takes them into the desert, the Judean desert away from the cities, to be away from the king and his ability to enforce his evil decrees.
As I mentioned, we talked about this in our episode on the phenomenon of prophets, which I think was called prophet mode of, as a super clever pun.
that end of Star Trek reference.
Yeah, that they were, so the prophets, there's all community of prophets and their wives and
their children, right, who live together in sort of a communal mode of living.
We see this reflected throughout the Hebrew Scriptures in a whole series of points.
Remember, there's the city of profits where Samuel is that's all goes down to, and then...
Rips off all his clothes and thrashes around on the ground.
And there's a Lysha
after the Prophet Elijah ascends into heaven as we were just talking about,
goes back to the community of the prophets.
So this community of prophets is a thing,
right, sort of in the background, all through.
Kind of in many ways like a monastery.
Yeah.
In many ways, sort of the template for monasticism actually.
Yeah, and so they go out into the desert to avoid Manasseh.
Manasseh brings back paganism and his revitalization of paganism allows Balaal.
Also sometimes spelled Bel-E-R just replacing the last L with an R.
It gives him a chance.
We've talked about Balaal before.
It means sort of the Eoclis one.
I remember we talked about...
some detail in the Antichrist episode about the man of lawlessness. That lawlessness is the
man of Balaal. But anyway, so Balaal means the yokless one, like the lawless one. So this is a
devil figure again in our second temple literature. He possesses a pagan prophet. He's able to
possess him because this pagan prophet is involved in pagan worship of demons in Israel.
and the
the prophet he produces or who he possesses is named Belkira, which is probably not what his
mom named him because Belkira and Arabic means Lord of evil. Yeah. So yeah, not a good baptism
name, folks. Yeah. We'll not baptize little baby Belkira. Definitely a villain for your next
RpG.
Yeah, yeah.
And that title, by the way, Lord of Evil or Belkira at Arbeck is one of the titles for
Samuel, the fallen archangel.
Yeah, we're going to, so we really do have to do a devil's episode.
So this is, you know, bad dude possessed by the devil basically.
is the idea here and Pizzest Belkira goes out to track down Isaiah.
because he's the prophet of God of the true God and they capture him and they put him in a
log and they saw him in two and
That is how Isaiah dies a martyr's death so he sort of murdered by this
demon possessed false prophet. Yeah, creepy
so
That's sort of part narrative part one
Okay.
So part two, this is the first of our Christian parts, is the material that's in chapter
six through eleven.
And this is an apocalyptic vision that Isaiah has.
Now you may be thinking.
Hold on now.
Oh, is he dead?
Yes.
Well, you may be thinking, oh, okay, so he died.
So is this like his soul goes up into heaven and has this vision?
No.
No, this is a prequel.
Yeah.
This is an apocalyptic vision that Isaiah had well before he died, well before he was martyred.
That is just recorded here.
So this section is from chapter 6 through 11 is often called the vision of Isaiah.
Yeah, although in a sense, this is kind of like the ascension proper sort of.
Yes.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah. Yeah. So essentially it is being used somewhat ambiguously.
Right. Refer to both the visions and his death.
Right. He does. Yeah, exactly. Exactly. Yeah.
So it recounts this apocalyptic vision where he's led by the angel of the Lord.
Right. The angel of Lord figure from the Hebrew Scriptures. On this journey through
to the 7-1-1-1.
where he sees all of these things and
recounts all of these things.
When he's talking about the angel, the Lord, the angel, the Lord shows up
and Isaiah comments, oh he's very different.
This angel is different.
He's different than all the angels.
Right, this is this very different figure, this higher figure, this greater figure
and refers to how he's very different from the angels that he saw all the time.
Yeah, it's kind of an interesting detail in the text that he sees angels
all the time and oh this one's different. But wait this this is a completely different
thing. And that's seeing angels all the time we've talked about with prophets before like
Elisha and Gahazi when he opens Gahazi's eyes to see all the angels. Yeah.
And applying the Elisha saw that all the time. That these very holy people sort of have
constant access to the spiritual world in a way that we don't. A sinner.
So he asks the angel of the Lord his name because he could see who's this, right?
This is totally different.
And he kind of says, well, I'll tell you my name at the end of our journey, spoilers,
it's Christ.
And this is one of the things where we know this is very obviously a Christian text, right?
It's not even like the Messiah.
like it's way more specific than that.
And this shows us, there shouldn't be too much of a surprise, right?
That we already in the first century have someone making the identification of the angel
of the Lord in the Old Testament with Christ because pretty early in the second century,
St. Justin Martyr says the same thing.
And just presents it as the Christian belief.
Yeah.
out any argument, he just says this is what Christians believe.
So it shouldn't surprise us that this was already around in the first century, at least somewhere.
Right. And so they go on this trip through the Seven Heavens. Interestingly,
what passes for hell where the evil angels are held is one of the heavens.
Right. Which kind of counterintuitive for us. Yeah, but it makes sense if you understand,
Right the devil is the prince of the powers of the
air. Yeah, sort of the lower levels. But yeah, like there's this sense that that
angelic powers, both good and evil are kind of in the air. And and this is of
course before the end of the world, right? So there's still kind of loose, you
know, well sort of yeah, kind of sort of somewhat. Yeah, but also that the
heavens, right, you would have to the seven heavens here, doesn't mean the sky.
Yeah, it's
literally. And it doesn't even mean the place where God is.
Right. It's associated with the sky in a, right.
And imagine what it really means is the spiritual world.
Right. Right.
Right.
It means the spiritual world, the seven levels of the spiritual world.
Right. Is really what we're talking about.
And they get in a fight with Samuel at one point,
because that guy is no good.
good. And then eventually once I get to this
7th heaven. This is where it gets really interesting. And I say really interesting. You might find all the 7 heavens interesting, but if you read a lot of this literature,
if you start reading a lot of apocalyptic literature, like you go through so many different visions of the 7 heavens that they're all different, right?
It kind of blends together after a while.
Yeah, and you know, but the part that's really interesting to me,
and I'm saying this essentially what I mean by this is...
as opposed to all those other ones, right?
What's really significant about this one in particular
is opposed to some of the things that you'll find
in many of them, if not all of them,
is when you get to the seventh heaven,
and you come to the throne of God,
and part of what I think makes this different
and unique and interesting is that
this is a first century Christian document, right?
So you're getting a window into the Christian view of this
at the earliest stage, at the apostolic stage.
Yeah, there's still the puzzles around.
when this is being done, when they arrive there, they're at the throne of God,
right, in the seventh heaven, the highest heaven. And in front of the throne of God, Isaiah sees the angels
and human saints, right, angels are holy ones too, but the human holy ones end them. The only one
of the human saints that's mentioned by
name is Enoch. But there's more, it says there's more of them there. Right? So these are the people
like Enoch. Right? And it says that they no longer have garments of flesh or garments of skin,
but they have new or renewed garments. Right? We've talked about garments as
skip before, right? This idea of the flash, the simple flash.
flesh that's subject to change, but also to death, mortality, corruption.
That's been changed or renewed to this new garment.
Think of St. Paul's language and for Scrintheons about being clothed with immortality.
This doesn't mean they don't have bodies anymore.
It means that their bodies are different, that they are changed.
referred to as being like the angels.
How about that?
And he sees that there are crowns and thrones and garments there waiting for future human
saints.
Yeah.
And those images come up over and over again in the text.
They talk about the crowns and the garments and the thrones.
Yeah.
Now this, you know, just if the Roman Catholic friends feel like I was picking up the
on them at the end of the last half. Now I guess I'll pick on our Protestant friends a little
bit or pick at a little bit, baby. But I think it's important. So again, this is first century.
Okay. This is first century use of language. So there has been a predominant view within
Protestantism.
that the language of clothing and changing clothing,
an old garment to a new garment,
this changing of clothes language,
especially as St. Paul uses it,
but also in other places where it occurs to the New Testament,
that this is talking about imputed righteousness,
that this is talking about sin in the sense of guilt
and deserving punishment.
on the one hand with the old garment and that the new garment is referring to righteousness
in some positive sense, like merit.
And so this is taken to be an image of justification or of salvation or of being born again, of accepting
Jesus, right, that the
The old garment that represents this sin and the need for punishment is taken off of
you and put on Christ and this perfect robe of Christ's righteousness and merit and goodness
is then put on you.
In what sometimes called the great exchange.
Here we have a real problem with that.
Because not only here do we see this language being used in a Christian text, and it not
meaning that at all.
Here it refers to mortality and immortality.
death and life.
And none of these garments is being worn by Christ.
Right. This is a garment there in heaven that's awaiting these people at the end of their journey.
And it would also like the image doesn't make sense if like this is Christ's garment because there's multiple sets of them around. Yes. Yes. You know, it doesn't work that way. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Now,
Someone who holds to that other view that predominant probably
of you might say to me, yeah well okay but essentially by say isn't in the Bible.
Okay. Right? And I'm going to say that the I'm going to hold out that the Bible uses it
in a different way. All right. Here's the problem with that. First Corinthians 15,
go read 1 Corinthians 15, St. Paul uses that language in 1 Corinthians 15 to mean exactly this.
Yeah.
Right.
So we have evidence both within the Scriptures and a Christian interpretive text outside of the Scriptures
showing this other usage of that language.
So to take this other view, that presupposes amongst other things.
I mean, there's all kinds of things we could say about this and argue about about this.
But,
Minimally, you have to presuppose that St. Paul uses the same language in two different places,
or three or four different places.
in completely different ways. Or, and at one of the ways he uses it, one of the ways he uses it
fits perfectly with the Christian use of that language contemporaneous to his epistles and
immediately thereafter, and the other way he uses it, the other kind of contradictory way he uses
that same language in other places, does not conform to the way Christians used it in the first and
second centuries.
Yeah.
It seems to me like he's probably always using it the same way.
And it's probably conspiment with the way Christians used it at the time he was using it and immediately thereafter.
That seems unlikely.
That's not checkmate Protestant.
Protestantism.
Ah, see, all Protestant doctors are wrong.
You need to become Orthodox.
I mean, you should.
I mean you should but uh but it is to say on the point
of that language, right? I think it's very difficult to argue that St. Paul himself was using
that language that way. You can argue it's a valid theological metaphor, it's derived
from something else somewhere else. Sure, sure, right? But to try to say that St. Paul
is using that language that way and say Romans, I think is a really hard argument to make,
light of everything. But you may be just...
is informed as me and disagree still.
That is as we said in the first half.
There ought to be totally hypocritical.
Just a little bit.
So in addition, some other little pieces we get here
at the end of this second section of the ascension of Isaiah,
the saints, the human saints, the human holy ones,
who are there.
with the angels, are they replacing the angels of the lower world?
Yeah, it's interesting because like the language that's there, there is this reference
then being lower, but there's also the angels on the right and on the left, and the ones
on the left are lower.
Right, so there's, it's this, you know, very, very, very old association of the right with
goodness and left with evil or whatever.
So, you know, but I mean, we've talked about this many times.
times the podcast before. So it's just, it's representing the same image of what we call
the left hand of God, you know, which we see in, in the image we see in heaven before
Ahab gets it. And, you know, that's how St. Gregory the theologist reads Job, but it's
that the angels gathered at God's right hand at his left hand. Yeah. And the ones at
the right are the right are his elect angels and the ones on the left are the other ones.
Yeah, exactly. So the idea here is that
the left ones, the lower ones, they have departed from obedience to God and humans are going to take their place.
Yes. And the particular way here, and this is some of these elements we're talking about here, you're going to find out in our last half,
are the reason why these two documents are related,
more even than the ascension assumption idea.
The reason that, or the way in which
they rebelled. So the inocic literature tends to focus on the giants of the Nephilim.
But the focus here of their rebellion is that they sought to be worshipped by humans.
They became the gods of the nations.
Yes, so this sort of the post-bable idea.
Right. That's sort of more of the focus here in terms of these angels and their judgment.
You also see quite frankly.
I think this is hard to avoid.
You see not just, you know, the Trinity in the sense of referring to the Father and the
Son and the Holy Spirit, which you get, for example, in Matthew 28, right?
Like, not just mentioning the names, not just mentioning the three persons, but in this
This first century document, late first century admittedly but still first century AD
Christian doc.
you see some detail and some depth into the doctrine of the Trinity as it will be sort
of codified if you want to use that language at the Council of NICIA.
Wow, and this is contemporary and is with a New Testament, everybody.
Yes.
So the text refers to the Great Glory, which is a reference to God the Father, because it's
saying the great glory that no one can look upon.
which is sort of God proper, right? Ophails the God, right? God the Father, right? And then there are two
other figures who Isaiah sees. One is Christ the Beloved, right? And when I said it's not ambiguous,
right? This isn't just the Messiah, right? This is Christ. It said that he is the one who descended
and then ascend it again to his former place.
So, it's very clearly referring to Jesus, right?
And we'll see it gets even more on the nose about that, but this is very clearly right
Christ.
And then he refers to, he says he sees the angel of the Holy Spirit.
Okay.
Now there are folks out there.
There are folks out there reading this.
who this kind of ruins their whole day, if they're scholars.
Because, remember, our going assumption, since at least the 19th century,
that our German friends has been that the doctrine of the Trinity evolved over the course of centuries.
Right. So finding a text like this for the first century.
That's a pain, right?
So this is a place where they read, he says he sees the angel of the Holy Spirit.
And they go, ah!
Here's our out.
We're going to say that this reads that this text is saying that the Holy Spirit is an angel.
Okay, now this isn't even need to take a logic course to get a PhD.
time. This is like SAT level reading comprehension. Okay. When he saw the angel of the Lord, did
that mean the text was saying that the Lord is an angel? Yeah. No. No. Right. If you go
out into the parking lot and you see the car of Father Stephen.
And you say, I saw the car of Father Stephen.
Does that mean you're saying Father Stephen is a car?
Okay, so this is what I mean by sub-logic course level.
Right?
Like that's not what that means.
Well, and also, frankly, if you look at chapter 8, so it's a few chapters before we're
talking about right now, it actually is.
It says, I thought this was really interesting. I'm just going to read it real quick.
It says he took me up into the sixth heaven and there were none on the left.
So right, this is the idea. There's the angels of left. The ones that left him left.
There were none on the left nor are thrown in the middle, but all were of one appearance and their praise was equal and strength was given to me
and I also sang praises with them and that angel also in our praise was like theirs and then this.
And there they all named the Primal Father and his beloved Christ and the
Holy Spirit all with one voice. So it's like father, son, and Holy Spirit explicit
years. We're all being worshiped by the angels and Isaiah is worshiping them with them.
But if you've based your whole career and all those articles you published on the idea
that niceine trinitarianism doesn't exist until the 4th century.
And you find it
in the first century, you've got to try to argue that it's not nice
in Trinitarianism. Yeah, come up with something. Or admit you're wrong, but we
can't do that. That's not possible. Yeah, right. So the fact that he sees the
angel of the Holy Spirit implies that this angel he is seeing is not the Holy
Spirit himself, obviously, but the Holy Spirit does not have.
bodily form. Yes, you don't see him. Right? So if he's going to see this in front of him, he also
doesn't see the great glory. That's why he just refers to God the Father as the great glory
that no one can look upon. Right? Then you're going to have to see some kind of representation of
the Holy Spirit. Right? Some kind of image of the Holy Spirit. So this angel or messenger is a
representation of the Holy Spirit.
that he sees, right?
It is definitely not saying that the Holy Spirit is an angel.
Yeah.
Right.
And the context in which he sees it is important, because he sees this worship being given,
worship is being given not only to the great glory, not only to God the Father, but also
to Christ and to the Holy Spirit.
Okay.
But he makes this important point.
point. That the worship that's given to Christ and the Holy Spirit, Christ and the Holy
Spirit then pass on to the Father. Right, they then pass on to the Father. Why is this
important? Well, this is the same principle, the same idea that lies behind in the formulation
of nicene trititarianism. What, St. Basil the Great?
Especially St. Basil the Great.
and say in this case, it is the great, and St. Gregory of Nissan is why there are not three gods.
St. Peter's the Great uses some important terminology with this. So part of the reason
why Christians are not tri-fists
among many, but one primary and very important one
right, is that Christians worship one God.
Who is that one God?
Christ is worship one God, as it says in the Nicene Creed, the Father, Almighty.
Father is the one God, and the worship that is given to Christ and the Holy Spirit,
St. Basil the Great says, the honor given to the image passes to the prototype.
Yeah, and Christ is described as the image of the Father.
The express image of God the Father, who is begotten of the Father, the Son is the image
of the Father by definition.
That's how Father and Son works, diplomatically.
And the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father as the image of the Father.
So the worship offered them passes on to God the Father.
And if you want direct Bible references to this, remember when St. Paul talks about Christ's
Thank you.
all things to the Father. This is how the early Christians understood what it
meant when Jesus said the Father is greater than I. Or when Jesus says this is
life that they know you the only true God. And Jesus Christ whom you said. He is
not there denying that he is God, right? That he is divine.
He is there affirming that there is one God the Father.
While also other texts affirm that Jesus Christ is God because He is the express image
of the Father, meaning everything that the Father is, He is also.
God from God, right, light from light, true God from, true God, right?
All of that nice in language.
So that principle that state basal the
great points to through that principle that the honor or give you these
branches of prototype, right? So he's making that distinction using Greek
philosophical terms, right? But he's making the same point that's being described
in narrative here in the ascension of Isaiah. Again, contemporaneous with the
New Testament. Contemporaneous with the New Testament, a Jewish Christian
source. Okay. This is also important. Get out of here.
with this, oh the Bible was written with a hebraic mindset and the church
fathers had a helemic mindset. Get out of here with that nonsense. Okay. They're
using different sets of terminology in different languages to describe the same
reality. Okay. That's what's happening. So the core element, at least a core
element of nice internitarianism is
here in a Jewish Christian work in the first century.
Lee centred by Zah, incontrovertibly.
Right? Is every element of nice
infinitarianism here in this one text?
No, of course not.
Right.
Right? Of course not.
But this core element is,
And I think frankly this by itself is enough to...
to validate the claim that the Council of Nicae makes
that what they taught was apostolic.
Because this at least shows that in the time of the Apostles
there were Christians who believed
what was proclaimed at Nicae.
It's impossible for me to prove every Christian did.
Sure.
Or that any particular Christian did.
But it was clearly believed at that time
by Christian.
Sorry, just about everybody.
Okay.
All right.
So then, let's say, what's the third part that's actually not the third part?
We have to talk at the very end of this section, then there's sort of a summary of the life of Christ.
Oh yeah, right.
All right.
That is, it's beyond on the nose.
It's very clearly dependent upon.
the Christian gospel, not necessarily any of the written, probably not any of the written
gospels.
It doesn't seem to be, there's not enough detail in it for you to say like, oh, this is
based on Matthew, right?
But there's enough detail that it's like, obviously, this is, especially combined with
everything else.
This is clearly a Christian document, right?
But the way it's presented, this is what's important about it, is that it's in
please.
presented in terms of, because remember our literary figure here is Isaiah. This is a vision Isaiah is having.
And so the idea behind this recounting of Christ's life is it's using terminology and things to connect it to the canonical book of Isaiah.
Yeah.
To try and say oh Isaiah in the canonical book of Isaiah was really talking about Christ. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, and you get stuff not just the Messiah in general. So you get stuff that is as you said so
on the nose. Like, for instance, it talks about him being a baby in Nazareth. Yeah. So like,
right, right. Yeah.
But this is connected to things in the canonical book of Isaiah to try to show that, right?
Jesus is the one who he was talking about. So there's this third part. This third part gets wedged
did to the first part.
The third part is called the Testament of Hezekiah.
And as the text now stands, and again, we're using the Charles
Ruth numbers, is chapter 3 verse 13 through the rest of chapter 3 and then all of chapter 4.
And it's been just kind of crammed in there.
Yeah, and again
Then obviously Christian 3 verse 15 refers to the Christian ecclesia, Christian church.
So I mean it uses the word Christian.
But this piece is another vision of Isaiah in which he sees, again, in very on the nose detail,
only the birth, life, death and resurrection of Christ.
but the coming of the Holy Spirit, the Apostles going and evangelizing the whole world, right?
So I mean this is clearly Christian, right?
But then he goes on in the vision to talk about the coming of the Antichrist.
And if you read the description of the Antichrist much like in the book of Revelation,
it's pretty clearly that the Roman Emperor Nero is kind of the model here.
Yeah, but that's what you'd expect.
respect at the end of the first century.
Sure.
Right. In the second half of the first century, everyone was using Nero as the model of the
Antichrist, including the Book of Revelation, which was written at that time too.
And then after the coming of the Antichrist, you have the resurrection of the dead,
you have the last judgment and then the beginning of the eternal kingdom.
Right.
So essentially his vision is the gospel.
Right. For all intents and purposes Isaiah sees the gospel in this vision and it's presented
that it's wedged in there so that they can say the fact that he had this vision, the
fact that Isaiah knew the gospel in advance, that's why Belial came and killed him. Yeah.
Yeah. That's why it gets crammed in there. That Belial didn't want anybody else to know
about this. So he...
goes and sort of assassinate Isaiah through Gori means.
Now it's important.
So this is again, we talked about this already
with sort of the idea of pseudopigrophy
as we were talking about some of these texts.
Right, modern readers tend to come to these texts
and assume that there's some kind of fraud
or falsification going on.
Right, this text is making the claim
that Isaiah had these visions and knew these things, right? That's not what's happening.
That's not what's happening. Yeah, it's more like Isaiah is a character that is being used
as a mode of interpretation of his prophetic book that's in the scripture of Isaiah. Yeah, exactly.
It's a way of saying, okay so.
Isaiah's prophecy connects with what we know from the Gospels,
and here's a way of talking about the connections between them.
Right. And so the reason these texts gravitate together is that you have this text just recording Jewish traditions of how Isaiah died.
Right. Right.
And then you have some Christian texts where Isaiah is used as a figure to represent the book of Isaiah,
and show the connections between that and
Christ. Right? What Isaiah prophesied and the death and resurrection of Christ and these other things.
The bodily resurrection, the last judgment, all of this. Right? And so they gravitate to each other.
Right? But this happens all the time, even in the New Testament. Right? In the New Testament,
it's very common to quote, say Moses says, and then it's just a quote from the Torah.
Yeah
Right, and sometimes what's being quoted isn't something that Moses said
Like the person Moses isn't the one who said it sometimes it's God who said it
Right, but they'll wait if they're quoting the Torah that just say Moses spoke saying
Right, and sometimes they'll quote Psalms that aren't even Psalms of David in the New Testament and say David says yeah
Yeah, yeah, it's because David as a figure is just used to represent
the Psalms. And Solomon is just a figure that's used to represent wisdom. Right? Yeah.
At some point I'm sure we'll go into this more detail on the show, but I hate to tell you
folks, the book of wisdom was written in Greek in the first century. And the fathers who
to quote it as refer to it as the wisdom of Solomon knew that.
You know how I know that?
do that? Because a lot of them listed as part of the new testament, not the old testament.
Yeah, I mean, this, this just underlines what pseudopigraca is in this period. It's not, you know,
an attempt to steal somebody else's name and pass their, your stuff off as theirs. It's using
them as a figure in some ways, maybe to invoke their authority, but in many cases like this,
as an interpretive device.
Right, you know?
So Isaiah here represents the book of Isaiah.
So you should read a statement like,
if you, a summary statement, like Isaiah
foresaw the birth, life, death,
resurrection and ascension of Christ.
Right, you should read that as what they're claiming
actually in this text is the
book of Isaiah prophesied the birth, life, death, resurrection, and ascension of Christ.
This is the correct way to read the book of Isaiah. Yes. So this is a way of doing
interpretation, a sort of narrative way of doing exegesis. Right? It is not making us a
historical claim about the historical Isaiah and what he knew and when he knew it.
Yeah, this is just like what we saw with Jubilees.
You know, Jubilees is a way of interpreting
and understanding Genesis and a little bit of Exodus.
You know.
Yeah.
And we'll talk about this more
because we're gonna see the same thing here
as we move into the third half
with in the assumption of Moses,
the way Moses is used as a figure in that text.
Exactly, exactly.
All right, well, we're gonna take our second and final break
and it'll be right back with the learn.
of spirits. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
I
Saint Paisio said, every day you should try to plant in your soul something spiritual
which will eject something worldly and sinful.
Replace the sinful images in your mind with holy ones.
AtheniteUSA.com offers holy icons for those wishing to plant something spiritual in their
souls.
Immaculate 22 karat gold leaf and apply it on solid wood.
A lifelong gift for yourself and someone you care for.
the code for base.
for free shipping. Come and see aponiteusa.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Daymak
and Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
And we're back. It's the third half of this episode of Lord Spirits. We're talking about,
we just discussed the ascension of Isaiah, and now we're going to be talking about the text called
the assumption of Moses. Or is it? Probably. Probably. If that is its real name. Yeah, we can't just assume that.
Yeah, so yeah, we do have to kind of start there.
So we have this tech.
right? We only have one copy of it. And it labels itself the assumption of
Moses. Okay. So from ancient sources, we have references to a book called the
assumption of Moses, to a text called the assumption of Moses, and to a text
The text called the test
of Moses. This text that we have while it is called the assumption of Moses, in
literary genre it is a testament. So we talked about the testament of the
12 patriarchs, we talked about how testaments are. These are the final words of
some biblical figure. Last will and testament. So this is the last words of Moses to
Joshua. That's what's in the
text that we have. So okay, in genre it's a testament, it calls itself the assumption of Moses.
We have these sources talking about the assumption of Moses and talking about the test of
Moses. Maybe this is the same book. You might think by two different names. Here's a
problem. St. Nicholas the confessor of God's Staten Opal, who we've mentioned before on
the show who made in the ninth century.
when he was the patriarch of Constantinople, made a list of books that were publicly read in all the churches,
meaning effectively canonical everywhere. Books which were read publicly in some churches but not others,
meaning were considered canonical in some Christian communities but not others.
and then books
that were to be read privately by everyone's consideration.
And these are all texts that were available to him
in the library constatinople.
So it's a very helpful list.
Shows us where things were at the night century.
He not only lists the names of the books,
but he lists their length in lines.
How many lines of text there are in the work?
Hmm.
How long it is?
And he has separate listings for the assumption of Moses and the testament of Moses
With different lengths like a major difference in length
So these are different texts for him which makes it clear that he had in front of him two different texts
Yeah, one of which he was calling the assumption of Moses and what he's calling the tester in a Moses
So these are not there are two different texts, right?
So which one?
is this that he had in front of him?
Well, also, there's work of fusion.
Yeah, of course, I get the question is how many lines in what language?
And yeah, yeah, yeah.
And so, um, yeah.
Well, we can't, we, we can't use that to figure it out because the one copy we have
of this text is missing the last third.
Oh, so we don't know exactly how many lines are at it.
Yeah.
in total. Now we do have, there is a quotation in St. Athanasius and a few more in some Byzantine
writers where they quote things that are in this text that we have and say they're quoting the
the assumption of Moses.
Okay.
So this is why we're calling it the assumption of Moses.
Right?
This is why we've chosen assumption rather than testament is the witness of state
affidacious to the text and these other busy teen authors and the fact that it
labels itself the assumption of months. But right. If you're gonna look this up
in Charlesworth, he calls it the testament of months. He calls it the testament. He makes the other decision.
Right. So just putting that out there. Yeah. And of course that side can argue, guess what's
in that.
last third that we don't have. Yeah, maybe that's the
assumption. The actual assumption of Moses. Yeah. Right. The
place where his body is actually taken up into heaven, we don't
have that part of the story. Right. Right. So Charles
Worth could say what we actually have is a testament. The
assumption piece is missing. Right. Now, our side can then
respond and say, well, actually
If you read the part we have, Moses refers to the fact that his body is about to be
assumed up to heaven in what we have.
So surely that was in the piece that's missing because it's telegraphed early, right?
But you can't be conclusive, right?
It's a test to know about the assumption and some other things.
Yes, we made a call, right?
But there's an issue there.
On top of everything else, the one manuscript we have is in Latin.
It's a Latin translation.
Thank you for watching.
seems to be a translation of a translation probably.
Yeah, because there's non-Latin phrases in there.
Latin from Greek from Hebrew probably is.
Right.
And the copy itself is from the sixth century.
And dug up in the 19th by an Italian.
We used to have none copies.
He found it.
they call it palimpsest, which means
Yeah, it's they use he found it's like a text that was erased.
And there's another text that was written on top.
So he read the erased parts, but it wasn't obviously perfectly erased,
which is why I get still see it.
So it was it was reused.
Yeah, because they didn't have erasers.
It's it's on vellum.
So you have to scrape it off.
Yeah.
So they reuse the vellum, which is animal skin.
A lot of it to ancient texts are this way, folks.
There's a lot of things that we have only in with their and polyamps.
Yeah, this is the word for today.
There you go, palimpsest.
Whenever someone says palimpsest,
scream real loud for the rest of the day.
Whew, not gonna be much screaming in most homes I don't think.
Um, it's gonna be deliberately goaded, right?
But so yeah, whatever texts,
St. Nicholas Forest was looking at would have been the Greek versions.
So yeah, again, right.
Yeah.
So, pretty much everyone agrees on the dating of it.
I said the copy is 6th century, but pretty much everyone agrees that this was written in the early 1st century AD.
So, for a couple of reasons. One reason is, there's nothing to point to this being a Christian text.
Yeah, but so but this would mean though like Jesus is alive and is
know, this is pre-Jordan, you know. Right. That's what early
first century was. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. He's been born. But there's
probably during the life of Christ himself. This was right. Yeah.
And so it seems pre-Christian. But also in the text that we have, a major portion of it is sort
of recounting the history of Israel and it kind of goes right up to the...
for century BC.
Right. Um, so no one thinks this is a mystical prophetic text.
So it was written after the events, it records, right?
Because I mean, it goes through the Hasmonean period, it talks about the Macabee,
it revolve, the Hasmonean, like it goes right up into the, so normally when you find
text like that. When you see apocalyptic texts used to recount history, it's
leading up to the time of writing.
And so everyone's pretty much an agreement that this text
is doing the same thing, all those other ones do.
And so if you take pre-Christian plus records
events from the first century BC,
you get beginning of the first century AD.
And pretty much everyone agrees.
Moses, as we mentioned at the end of the second half,
Moses is used here to sort of represent.
the Torah to represent what he wrote in this, in giving this recounting of history. And we should
remember that in the Hebrew scriptures, the Old Testament proper, the books from Joshua
through second kings or fourth kingdoms are referred to as the Deuteronomistic history,
because they're not objectively describing the history of Israel, the describing the history of
Israel from the perspective.
perspective of, in particular, the book of Deuteronomy.
Right? And the blessings and cursings that come upon Israel based on their faithfulness or faithfulness regarding the commandments of the Torah. Right?
That's the basis. And so this is a similar kind of thing going on. Right? This is put into the mouth of the person Moses, but Moses is here representing the Torah, representing that perspective on history.
Um.
As we mentioned,
genre wise, this is a testament.
This is Moses speaking to Joshua before he dies
within the frame story.
During that, as I mentioned,
he talks about the fact that his body's about to be
assumed into heaven.
So I mean, that's how part of how we know that that,
some version of that was in the piece that's missing.
Right.
He,
now again,
This is the second time. This one's not quite as bad as the angel of the Holy Spirit, but it's not good either.
So some scholars have looked at this text and said, oh look, this text is saying Moses predicted
in detail all these things that were going to happen over the next, depending on where you put Moses,
millennium and a half millennium and a quarter, right?
This text is claiming...
that the historical Moses knew all of these things.
Well, if the historical Moses knew all of these things for sure,
then that would mean they were all set in stone.
What?
And therefore, whoever wrote this text with some kind of,
I don't know, early Jewish Calvinist or some kind of fatalist
who believed that all of Israel's history was set in stone beforehand.
Because that's how prophecy totally works.
even given that idea.
Yeah, not only is that not how prophecy works as we were just saying at the end of the last half right
This text is not making a historical claim that Moses really said this. Yeah, this is not you know untold secrets of the right prophecies
Right Moses is here. They're not trying to scam people. They're not trying to trick anyone. They're not trying to start their own Jewish sect
Moses is here being used. He's speaking for the Torah. He's a literary vehicle
This is very common in apocalyptic literature.
People use a kind of apocalyptic,
prophetic recounting of history
in order to comment on their own times.
It's kind of a subroso way.
You don't just come out and say,
the current high priest is garbage man.
He's corrupt.
because
bad things happen to you if you go and say that publicly, right?
Or you got start talking trash about the Romans, right?
Bad things happen to you, but you produce a text where you have, I don't
I'm just randomly picking Daniel, saying all this stuff about the horrible
Greeks, right?
Like, or the horrible Babylonians.
and the Babylonians are the Greeks in your text just happened to sound a lot like the Romans?
Yeah.
You could convey your meaning, right?
Or you talk about the Assyrians, wink wink, right?
Like, I mean, this is, again, part of this, I think, is the assumption that like just ancient
people were stupid and weren't capable of kind of nuance, right?
Because like, you know, do you think anybody would go and read Georgia LR Wells animal farm and say,
well, this text is claiming that animals can talk and form complex societies on farms.
Of course not.
He's very clearly using these animals that their relations to the farm, the context of critiquing to talitarianism.
Right? Like...
we get that, right? And there's no reason why someone in the first century AD
couldn't do something similar. And why readers of that text in the first
century couldn't understand what the author was doing because they're just as
smart because we are. This is just should be basic kind of stuff. Now that...
said, right, the author, like pretty much all Jews, I'm sure believed in the
prophets of God, right? And part of this narrative recounting of history is that
God is doing things, right? God is a mover within history. God is doing things
and he's bringing good out of evil and he's right, he's doing things. Providence
is a thing. It's real, right? So this is not to say the other extreme, right?
away from like fatalists on one hand because it's a
random event, right? It's not random events. That's that flies it, that contradicts the
text just as much. Texts are not saying the events are random. Right? There's a purpose
and a meaning to these events that the text is trying to bring out, but that doesn't imply
some kind of predestination or worse fatalism, right? Either. It's in between. Not everything
his extreme.
One of the central sort of interesting themes in the recounting of history
is that unlike some so some overviews like if you look at the Deuteronomistic history,
you probably have to conclude that the focus there is on different kings. That's why we call it
first and second kings, right? There's good kings and evil kings. It's sort of the fate and
fortunes of Israel.
as it's recounted there, the Deuteronomistic history sort of ebb and flow with who the king is.
Right? You have David as the archetypal good king, whether archetypal evil kings, you have Josiah who reforms it. Right?
That's sort of the focus. With this recounting of history in the assumption of Moses,
the blame is placed more on the tribe of Levi for everything going wrong.
wrong. Because everything goes wrong. They end up in exile. They end up out of the Romans.
Right. Why is everything a mess?
because the priesthood became corrupted.
And so when the priesthood became corrupted
and the worship of Israel became corrupted,
that was the first domino with all these other things going wrong.
So the evil kings and from the perspective of this text,
the evil kings, the injustice,
all the other horrible sin and everything that was going on in Israel
was the fruit of the poison tree of the false worship
and the corrupt
priesthood. So that said if we're looking at this being written in the early part of
the 1st century AD, right, it starts to materialize, okay, using this historical commentary
as a way of commenting on the present time, this is probably directed against the sageses
against the current high priesthood priests, right, who control the temple, who are definitely
corrupt or beyond.
corrupt, right?
Not only were they collaborating with the Romans to keep their power,
we've talked before on the show about how they used the temple tax to,
for their family to take possession of 70% of the land in Jutea that wasn't owned by the Romans,
belong to the high priestly family.
Because they confiscated it for back taxes, by levying temple taxes that they knew the people couldn't pay.
and then they went to work as tenant.
farmers on what used to be their land. And it wasn't just that it used to be their land,
like they used to own it. This was land given by God in the Torah to their families.
Yeah, these are the allotments.
Yes. And they took it for themselves. So this is sort of the image of ultimate correct, right?
So again, standing up in Jerusalem and publicly denouncing the high priestly family, not good for
for your health and well-being, right?
But this is a way to do that, right?
By showing...
You're saying this is the problem.
Israel's history is a corrupt priesthood.
And that also tells us the likely circles out of which this text emerged.
Probably the Pharisees.
Fairacies are of course opponents of the Sadducees, but not just that.
Remember, as we said when we were talking in the first half about the assumption of Moses'
body of the heaven.
This is directly intimately connected to the idea of the bodily resurrection.
Yeah.
So it's very likely that this text emerged from ferrous aic circles and this sort of sharp
critique of the temple's corrupt priesthood is aimed at the sagicies at the time, right,
through this vehicle.
And Moses is being used to represent what the Torah has to say about this corrupt priesthood.
Right.
And so then at the end of it though, or the end of what we have, the end of the
test of it part, there is this sort of final prophecy that Moses games because
of course his recounting of what for the author was history is presented as
Moses prophesying to, but you jump from the first century BC and their
kind of history, you jump to the end of days. You jump.
to the day of the Lord. And so there is this final concluding prophecy about the day of the Lord
that is quite interesting. Yeah, I'm going to read it and everybody just listen closely and
maybe don't remind you of something as I'm reading it. Don't worry, we will tell you what it should
remind you of after I'm done reading it, but I just want to put it in front of you first.
Yeah, okay, so it starts like this. Then his kingdom will appear throughout his whole creation,
then the devil
have an end. Ye sorrow will be led away with him. Then will be filled the hands of the messenger
who is in the highest place appointed. Ye he will at once avenge them of their enemies.
For the heavenly one will arise from his kingly throne. Ye he will go forth from his holy
habitation with indignation and wrath on behalf of his sons. And the earth will tremble, even to its
ends till it be shaken. And the high mountains will be made low. Ye they will be shaken as enclosed
that
with they fall. The sun will not give light, and in darkness the horns of the moon will flee,
yea, they will be broken in pieces. It will be turned wholly into blood, yea, even the circle
of the stars will be thrown into disarray. And the sea, all the way to the abyss, will retire,
to the sources of waters which fail, yea, the rivers will vanish away. For God most high will surge forth
the eternal one alone. In full view, will he come to work vengeance on the nations, yea, all
all their-
will he destroy? Then will you be happy, O Israel, and you will mount up above the
necks and the wings of an eagle. Ye, all things will be fulfilled, and God will
raise you to the heights. Ye, he will fix you firmly in the heaven of the stars
and the place of the habitations. And you will be hold from on high. Ye, you will
see your enemies on the earth, and recognizing them, you will rejoice, and you will
give thanks, yay, you will confess your creator.
So.
I mean, there's a lot going on here that's kind of end of the world sort of imagery, like
you see in the Gospels, frankly, which, you know, not written yet.
Possibly some of the writers not even born yet, but so yeah, they didn't make all that
stuff up.
But yeah, you get this image of God rising up from his throne and he's about to enact
vengeance, right?
And the idols of the nations are going to be destroyed.
And then finally you get the image of him saying the powers of the Sun and Moon are crushed, crushed.
Yeah. Oh yeah, the earthquake, the earthquake, foundations of the Earth was shake.
Yeah, and then you, Israel, will be raised up to the heights and be fixed firmly in the heaven as the stars
and the place of their habitations. Right. So it seems like this is a kind of
expansion on Psalm 82 in a number of ways.
You get God enacting judgment.
Well, he arises.
He arises, right?
A rhizogod.
Remember the Psalm 82, a rhizogod.
Yeah, and even the language of God will surge forth.
This is this sort of, you know, in Greek, right?
You know, Anastah,
grise up, right?
Uprising.
Yeah, I mean, it's not exactly the same.
It's not just a retelling of the song.
Right, there's a lot of eschatological imagery in here, but definitely something going on here that's very similar in a lot of ways
And interpreting it is him judging the gods of the nations right the idols are gonna be destroyed
And then you get the bit about putting on newdened stars
Yeah, the holy ones in their places
destroyed and yeah, and they're exalted as stars
up into the heavens of their places
And the right to stand before the road.
God, the Archangel's did the Fallen gods or gods' ashes are punishing it and...
Yeah, it says like like in the Charles Ruther says you will see your enemies on the earth, but I mean what is the earth right like it's that sense of
Errits, the underworld in Genesis 3.
So that's the end of the world expectation and prophecy here that we get depicted at the beginning of the first century AD.
Right in this Jewish source.
And again, it shows us how that was understood, which is very much how it's understood and used liturgically in the Orthodox Church on Holy Saturday.
as prophecy.
So, as we mentioned, we talked about way back at the first half so long ago now.
We talked about his reference in Jude verse 9 to the devil and St. Michael contesting
over the body of Moses, right?
And of course, that would be in the piece that's missing.
Right?
Yeah.
All this
about what this actual dead body is in the piece that's missing.
We do have a decent reason to think that was in this text because the earliest commentators
that we have on the Book of Jude.
So as you might imagine, there's not just mounds and mounds of commentary on the Book of
Jude.
It was not my time.
much to it anyway, it's really a short text.
But the earliest commentaries we have on the book of Jude,
we have earlier quotations from it.
But I mean, places that comment on Jude verse 9, frankly.
The earliest people who comment on Jude verse 9,
and that we still have, there's still extent today,
are a certain fellow named Galatius of Cizicus.
Okay.
New.
I know you all read everything he's written.
And origin, everyone's favorite non-saint.
They're the earliest ones in the third century, who comment on Jude verse 9.
And both of them connect this reference to Saint Michael, the devil contesting over the
body of Moses.
to a text they call the assumption of Moses.
So of course, our case that that was included
in the missing portion of this text
is based on our case that this text
is the assumption of Moses.
Right, so that's not 100%.
But I think that's pretty good testimony
that what we have is
two-thirds of the text that contains the tradition
St. Jude is referring to.
Yeah.
Right.
That if we had the whole thing, it would include that element.
Now, that doesn't mean, by the way, we certainly can't say
for certain that St. Jude is quoting this text.
Right.
That would be going way too far.
Because we can't even demonstrate that what he's referring to
in this text 100%.
Right.
And there's probably an oral tradition element here too, right?
Where the idea that that happened precedes this actual text, right?
And so could have a common source, say,
Jude could just be referring to the tradition that underlies this, etc., etc.
But there it is.
Yeah.
All these things on the table look a little similar to each other or a lot similar.
Yeah, so there's...
reason to put them on the table together.
Yes.
Yeah.
So I think the main theme that is my takeaway from this is this question of, I mean, we,
it's funny, like we talked about ascensions and assumptions at the beginning and even
those categories don't totally fit exactly everything we're talking about.
Although of course with Moses, I think the assumption is a pretty clear thing.
That's the tradition.
Right, even though it's not that part doesn't show up in this text that we just talked about that has that name.
Because we, it's parts are missing.
But I think the thing that I want to come away with is this notion of the exaltation of the human person.
Right.
And this I think is particularly important because of this, and we've talked about this a bunch of times on the show, but I think it bears repeating.
especially from another angle in this case. This idea that Christianity believes that you go to heaven
when you die, if, fill in the blank here, you know, if you're a good person, if you ask Jesus
into your heart, if you, you know, whatever it is, right? If you've done the thing, then you go to
to heaven when you die, period and of story.
And I know for well that...
That is not the official teaching of most churches or definitely not Orthodox, definitely not Catholic, definitely not most Protestants.
But it is, however, an extremely common theology that people have, really, really common.
That this is what the afterlife is about, right?
Heaven and Hell when you die, and that's the end.
And oh yeah, oh by the way, there's going to be a resurrection.
in some day. And I think the problem is that it's even if people do mention that, it's a
by the way, right, that the hope of the resurrection is not the key vector of the way that a lot of
people think about the afterlife, the life after this life, right? And that there is the
possibility of bodily assumptions.
right, that there is the possibility of bodily ascension.
Even though for most of us, certainly bodily ascension
is not going to happen to us, right, which is being taken up
to be with God, even while we're still alive in this life,
not having died, you know, as Enoch and Elijah did, right?
And even though the bodily assumption that Moses experienced
experience that their Tokyo's experience
even though that is not going to happen in the same way for most of us, it is actually
going to eventually happen for the righteous. And I want to make a disambiguation here,
of course, because everyone is going to be raised from the dead, the righteous and the
wicked. As Christ says, the righteous to eternal life and the wicked to eternal condemnation
or damnation depending on your translation.
So everyone is going to be raised from the dead.
Everyone will have their souls and bodies put back together,
but the righteous, their bodies will be changed.
And that's really what this assumption is about.
Assumption into heaven is not about a change of place.
Now it's depicted visually.
Like the imagery that we have is of a change of place.
But it's interesting if you-
think about the assumption of Moses actually, we don't even have, like, I don't know.
Is that even an icon?
I mean, I've seen icons actually of the devil and Michael battling over the body of Moses.
I've seen that it's apparently a relatively rare, but I have seen icons, a friend of mine
who's an iconographer sent me some pictures of that.
But you don't get the assumption of Moses in terms of like a flight up into heaven.
And of course, for the Orthodox, the Dormition of the Theatokos is not depicted as a flight up into heaven.
And so the imagery is not that.
But even if you want to think of it as in terms of going from one elevation to another,
that's still not the point. It's not about a change of place.
This is about, as St Paul says, being caught up...
to be with Christ in the clouds, which doesn't mean we're going to all hover up rapture style into the air.
Sorry, dispensation lists. Sorry, everyone who's been affected by that theology, which is bunk.
Rapture theology is bunk.
What it's interpreting badly is the language and Scripture that human beings, when they're raised from the dead
and those who happen to be still living in this life when the end comes, when the true end comes,
that the right sister
bodies will be changed. They're going to be exalted. We're going to cast off mortality and put
on immortality. This is the the crowns and garments and thrones that we talked about in the
Ascension of Isaiah that is over and over again in that text. And we see that kind of language
in the in Revelation. We see it in Saint Paul. And we of course we have Christ himself saying that
humans will become equal to the angels, the righteous be equal to the angels, the sons of the
the resurrection be equal to the end.
That's the destiny of Christians.
That's the destiny of the faithful, bodily resurrection, and then this exaltation of the human person,
in which we will still certainly have material bodies, but they will be changed.
We don't know exactly how, but they will be changed.
St. Paul makes the comparison between a seed and a plant, which I think is a great image,
great image because...
If you've ever planted a seed and then you see the plant that comes, those two things don't look anything like each other.
But we know that they're the same thing.
That seed you put in the ground broke apart and became that plant.
It's the same thing.
And even if you were to do like a DNA test on it, you would see that it's the same thing.
But it's radically changed.
And St. Paul says that the bodies that we have now, or like the seed,
And the bodies that the faithful will have in the age to come are the
plant. And I think seeing that clearly and understanding that clearly puts a
shape to our Christian hope that is much more vivid and much more motivating in
terms both of trying to live according to the commandments of Christ and also
in terms of our evangelistic necessity. It's much more powerful vision of what
the life of the
to come is then simply going to heaven when you die. That is a very static, a very flat way
of understanding the age to come. And frankly, it's wrong. It's just incorrect, right? Not just
technically incorrect, but it's just incorrect. It's just way too limited and reduced and so forth.
that the life of the age to come for the faithful is going to be...
dynamic and active and
exalted and glorious, right?
Like part of the value of these apocalyptic visions is we have a glimpse
of what the possibilities for human beings really are.
To take the place of the angels, to be set among the stars.
Right? And if that sounds like pagan to you, right?
If that sounds like your, oh, Greek mythology talked about people being made into constellations.
...
That's not what that meant, but they were,
they were correct in the sense that human
exaltation to be like the stars,
that is to say, like divine beings,
that that is a possibility.
What the Greeks and all the other pagans
who talked about this stuff got wrong
was number one, it's not done through great feats of glory.
Right? You're not trying to oppress the gods
so that you get to become one of them.
And number two, it's actually available to everybody,
not just to emperors and sons of gods and whatever.
It's
available to everybody, including the lowest slave, the smallest child, the most abused,
stomped-on person in the world can become like the stars.
And in fact, they probably have a better shot at it, frankly, than those who are glorious
upon the earth. They have a better shot at it. When Christ came, he came as humble.
He came as humble.
and thus showed us the way.
So I think the value in looking at texts like these
is that they help us to see more clearly
what it is that we as humans can be.
This is our actual possibility.
And the key to getting there
is with the grace of God to be faithful,
Three, pen.
every day to follow the commandments, to say not me, but you to actually love your neighbor
and to worship the Lord Jesus Christ with His Father and the Holy Spirit.
Is that my cue?
That's your cue.
Period.
Amen.
Yeah, so I want to talk a little bit about picking up what we were talking about at the
end of the first half.
Long, long time ago, so long we can't remember when.
Talking about intellectual humility, which for some of us at least, including myself
and that may be the hardest kind of humility.
As I may have said on the show before, I talk a lot.
Like so, I do like this, I do a Bible study, I preach, I talk to people, I teach classes, I do all those stuff.
So I remember saying things, but I have trouble very often remembering where and when I said them.
So I ended up repeating myself a lot and things.
But as I may have said on this show in the past,
I have...
for literally decades now.
I have been reading Nietzsche during Lent.
Bless you.
To help me work on my intellectual humility
and sort of beat my reason over the head for a while,
and try and enforce it into submission.
I mean just to give
an example of what I mean by that, like how that would work.
You know, a manual can't say, there are these certain things that just have to be true.
We have to presuppose them because if they're not true, then sort of logical thought and reason become impossible.
And Nietzsche's response to Kant on that point is, who said rational thought and reason were possible.
And so it's a way of reminding myself repeatedly that all the things I think I know for sure,
I really don't know.
And all the things that I think I figured out, I don't really have figured out.
And all the things I think I totally comprehend and understand, I don't really understand and don't really comprehend.
which is hard to really...
convince yourself of. That's why I have to keep doing it repeatedly. We, especially now,
and this isn't just as modern people. This is a very contemporary thing. I'm saying this
as somebody of the United States, but I don't think it's all that different in most of the
other places where people are going to be listening to this. I have entered an era in
which
We take X files and Stone Cold Steve Austin way too seriously and we don't trust anybody.
Except ourselves.
We have an unbelievable amount of trust in ourselves.
And our own ability to understand things, and figure things out, and do our own research,
and find the truth ourselves, and get to the bottom of things.
But we don't trust any
everybody else. And if we don't trust anybody else in terms of just other individual
humans, once you start getting groups of people together, we trust them even less if
that's possible. And when those groups of people form institutions, we trust them even
less than that, if that's possible. There's a basic problem with that. And that's that
we still have to live.
We still have to, for our lives every day, we still have to do this, and you can't actually
live like that.
I just took a plane flight last week, I'm taking another one this week.
I don't want to.
I hate flying, but that's another topic.
But I think, honestly, if I'm honest with myself, one of the things I don't like about flying,
that Dr. C. Parker's about it is that
But I'm sitting there on a plane.
I can't pretend I'm in control of anything.
I have to trust this plane.
It's probably very old, and may or may not be well-maintained.
I have to trust the pilot that he knows what he's doing
and is managed to get some sleep and his co-pilot.
I have to trust that the maintenance group
did what they were supposed to do
that were properly fueled up.
that I don't like it.
right? When I'm driving in my car, I'm also having to trust in all kinds of things regarding the car and the maintenance that's been done on it and my own attentiveness of that maintenance.
But I at least have to give myself the illusion of control because I'm driving. I mean, I'm not controlling all the other motorists on the road.
So I'm not really, but I can pretend. Can't pretend on the plane.
Because we're obvious that I'm being forced to trust.
And the more we're honest about our lives, the more we are
our lives are more like being on a plane and less like being the commander of our own destiny
in every respect. So we constantly have to trust other people, even groups, even institutions,
just a function, everything.
And I think the only array around the various impasses at which we find ourselves
community wise is not to continue to deny the fact that we have to trust, but to at the
same time become intentional about the fact that we have to trust somebody and become
intentional about who we trust. Who do we believe?
Usually when people decry the lack of trust in our modern society,
they're comparing it to like an imaginary version of post-World War II pre-Vietnam war history,
at least in the United States, where there was trust in institution.
People quote unquote, believe science, right?
So they're decrying the fact that we don't believe scientists anymore,
or that we don't believe newscasters and journalists
anymore or that we didn't write. Let me be honest, those probably weren't the best people to trust in the first place.
But there are institutions and people we could trust, not because they're perfect, not because they never make mistakes.
You can trust God, you can trust Christ,
because he'll never make mistakes.
But his church is made up of humans.
And the clergy is made up of people like me who are sinners and are unreliable and will
make mistakes and will have bad days.
Sometimes give you bad advice.
But when you make the decision, this is the other piece.
When you make the decision not to trust people and institutions, even institutions that
God is a staff.
even people that God has given some level or degree or area of authority. You are
directly choosing then rather than trusting them because you got to trust somebody to
trust yourself. To trust your own ability to know and your own ability to understand
and your own ability to work things out. Any confidence you pull away from everyone
else is gonna go there.
If you start to, if you start to lose confidence in yourself without putting it in anyone else,
then you're in real trouble because then you can't function at all.
But the intellectual humility comes in in the realizing that I can't trust myself.
Remember that thing I just said about being a sinner?
That doesn't just apply to the advice I give other people. That applies to my own understanding.
And my own ability to decide what's right and what's wrong and what I should and shouldn't do.
what I shouldn't should
and say, I think of it in a situation.
If you listen to this show, you know,
I have no clue what I should and shouldn't say.
I think it and I say it for the most part.
And so I'm not trustworthy.
I'm one of the least trustworthy people I know in that regard,
in terms of who I myself can trust.
Right.
The most.
untrustworthy in general, person I know, is probably more trustworthy when it comes to me.
It's telling me the truth about who I am and what I do than I am in my own impression of
myself.
And so it's not just, I know when we talked about this at the end of the first half, there
probably people who are saying, you know, there he goes attacking Protestants.
on the issue of trusting the church, right?
But it's not just about that.
It's not even primarily about that.
It's about things far more basic
and where we put our trust.
So why we have spiritual fathers in the Orthodox Church?
So before I make an important decision,
I can get a second opinion.
So when I realize I've messed up,
I can get some advice about how to maybe try to start fixing it.
And not mess up again, at least not the same way.
I'll find it the way.
That's why we live in a church community and are part of a community.
Living in a community instead of living by yourself and visiting a community.
Living in a community puts all of these bumpers and barriers and frames around everything
you do.
That's where you learn living in a community, what some of the things are at least that
you should think it not say.
You probably shouldn't think them at all, but you definitely shouldn't say them.
Right?
Where you can learn the things that you don't do.
That's where you learn where there are lines that you don't cross.
That's how you learn how to live and how to function.
But doing that means you have to put some trust in the community and the people around you.
to enter into that in a trusting way rather than a distrust.
way rather than in a skeptical way. I think that's not only important in how we
approach like what church should I belong to, right? Not that that's not that's
super important but again more basically what do I do? How do I live my life?
right has to start with trusting the people around me. The people
who I care about and who care about me,
people I'm in a relationship with.
And as to start with,
not being skeptical of everything they say and do,
how do you be skeptical of something someone does?
You read all kinds of motives into it
that probably aren't there.
Speculate.
You, rather than assuming everyone is an honest actor,
you assume everyone is a bad faith actor.
This is where it starts.
We have to do that to live.
We have to start being intentional about it.
And we have to start trusting other people.
The people God has put in our lives more than we trust ourselves and our own ability to
think things through and our own ability to understand.
ultimately the truth is Christ. Ultimately the truth is God.
God whom we cannot comprehend. God who we cannot even frame correctly in human words.
So in the face of the truth being something we can't understand or comprehend,
what we're left with is trust. Amen. Well, that's our show this time around. Thank you very much
everyone for listening. We weren't live this time, but and we will.
be live next time. God willing we'll be live again in someday. We'll come live again in July.
But we'd like to hear from you. You can email us at Lord of Spirits at agentfaith.com. You can
message us at our Facebook page. You can also leave us a voicemail at speakpipe.com slash
storm spirits. And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find
Parish head over to orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy this for our live broadcast.
normally on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Fish don't fry in the kitchen. Beans don't burn on the grill. It took a whole lot of
try just to get up that hill. If you're on Facebook you can follow our page. You can join
our discussion group. Leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but more importantly than that please
share the show, the friend who is going to benefit from it. And finally be sure to go
to www.ancientfaith.com.strokestoport and help make sure we in lots of
other AFR podcasters stay on the air. Now we're up in the big leagues getting our
turn it back. As long as we live it's you and me baby. Ain't nothing wrong with that.
Thank you, good night. God bless.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener supported
presentation of Ancient Faith Radio. And I be held and I heard the voice of many
angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders and the number
of them was ten thousand times ten thousand than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice,
worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and
glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11